messed around he's nice
messed around he's nice
and
and
a
a
Today we are inviting Professor Zhong Sunlin from the Department of Geological Sciences, National Taiwan University
今天我們是邀請了這個台大地質科學系的中孫林教授
Then my child will introduce it
那我孩子要把它介紹一下
He was born in 1959 and is now 54 years old
他是1959年生的現在54歲
I won't say anything about this girl
這個女孩子的話我就不講了
Then he received his Ph.D. from the Department of Geology, National Taiwan University in 1990.
那他是1990年台大地質系獲得博士
We sometimes emphasize now and sometimes
我們有時候現在有時候會強調一下
The PhDs we train in Taiwan are also world-class.
我們台灣培養的博士也都是世界級的水準
He should be the same as our rebel headmaster Yang
他應該跟我們的楊叛直校長都一樣
That's called MIT
那是所謂MIT
Mate in Taiwan
Mate in Taiwan
PhD is from Taiwan
博士是從台灣拿的
Then the Ph.D. that I got now continues to teach at National Taiwan University
然後現在拿的博士繼續在台大任教
But from 1992 to 1993 to the University of Rennes in France
但是92年到93年到法國的雷恩大學
postdoctoral research
就博士後研究
This one who came to Australia in 7 years
就7年也到澳洲的這個
Tasmania is an island south of Australia.
就是塔斯馬尼亞在澳洲南邊有一個島
is an island twice the size of Taiwan
是比台灣兩倍大的島
there are universities
那裡有大學
that mineralogy is famous
那個礦物學很有名
where they visit
他們在那邊訪問
After returning to China, he has been teaching at National Taiwan University.
然後回國以後一直還在台大任教
In 2001, our Central Plains Institute of Earth Sciences also
2001年也是我們中原地球科學所的
Incarceration Fellows at the Institute
這個研究所的監禁研究員
His specialty is the dynamics of this geochemical
他的專長是這個地球化學的動力學
Phonics with Vulcan Circle
以火神圓成音學
Probably today's speech probably has something to do with this
大概今天的演講大概都有這個跟這個有關
he took it three times
他拿過三次
three times at most
三次就最多了
Three Distinguished Research Awards
這個三次傑出研究獎
And this American Geological Society meeting
還有這個美國地質學會的會事
Then Ministry of Education Academic Award
然後教育部的學術獎
Ministry of Education's National Award
教育部的國家獎座
Then Taiwan University Chaired Professor
然後台大獎座教授
most importantly international
最重要的是國際
National Science Council's Public Collaboration Research Program
國科會的公領研究計畫
Our National Science Council's Public Collaboration Research Program
我們的國科會的公領研究計畫
is to train Taiwan's academic leaders
就是培養台灣的學術領導人
to the international level
到國際的這個水準
His public policy is
他的公領計畫就是
This name is similar to the name of this project
這個名稱類似這個計畫的名稱
This is probably what he wants to introduce today
他今天要介紹的大概就是這個
the name is called
這個名稱叫做
His public project is called
他的公領計畫叫做
Across Tibet to study Earth's in comparison
越過西藏對比研究地球的
Three Generations Created by Two Collisions
兩大碰撞的造三代
This is more strict
這是比較嚴格的
or more academically
或者比較學術的說法
This is not an academic statement
這個不是學術的說法
and crossed Tibet
而且是越過西藏
hug medical
抱醫療
research error
研究失誤
this enjoys the scenery
這個欣賞風光
study geology
研究地質
our warm applause
我們熱烈的掌聲
welcome is fair
歡迎是公順的
Is there a sound?
有聲音嗎
have
有
Also share the introduction
也分享一下介紹
thank you all
謝謝大家
Everyone, I didn't expect so many people to come today
大家,沒想到今天有那麼多人來
Teacher Peng said that I admire the teacher profession most in National Taiwan University
彭老師說我在台大最敬佩的老師職業
So he asked me to come and I couldn't refuse him
所以他要我來我都沒辦法拒絕他
Actually, I'm not very good at giving customer service speeches.
其實我不太會做客服的演講
But since it's here, there's a story in the middle
但是既然來了中間有一個故事
Let me just say by the way that you Xu made today's opening remarks
我就順便說一下有許當初今天的開場白
The contact for this speech was actually at the beginning of October last year
這個演講的聯絡其實是去年的10月初
Vice President Peng's secretary will contact me
彭副院長的秘書跟我聯繫
I just want him to contact me and say to contact me in early October
我就想他跟我聯繫說10月初聯繫
Then he said that he would make a speech at the end of October.
然後說10月底要做一個這個演講
I just say
我就說
Oops, is that because the person in front didn’t tell me to call me?
哎呀那是不是前面人不講找我來電檔
But because Mr. Peng wanted it
但是因為是彭老師要的
So I dare not refuse
所以我也不敢拒絕
I said ok then I'll come
我就說好吧那我就來
That
那
When I made an appointment, I found out that he was actually talking about this year.
具體約時間的時候我才發現他其實是講今年
Contact in October last year will come this year
去年的10月聯絡要到今年
So I waited in line for a year to get here to speak
所以我是排隊排了一年才排到這個來演講的
So you have to wait in line first
所以先排隊也不能不來
Actually, I should be going at this time
其實我這個時候應該是要去
We're having that 125th annual meeting in Denver right now.
現在正在Denver開那個125週年的年會
That special section with an Iranian address in it
那個會裡面有一個伊朗地址的那個special section
The host originally asked me to give a talk
那個主持人原來要我去給個talk
But I said I had scheduled a speech a year ago
但是我說我早一年以前就已經定了一個演講
so i can't go to that
所以我不能去那個
I just have to come to this
我只必須要來這個
what i want to talk about today
那我今天要講的東西
Because look at that time is two hours
因為看那個時間是兩個小時
I don't know how long I'm going to talk
我不曉得我到底要講多久
But everyone line up
但是大家排一排
Then I also sneaked to the Internet to have a look
然後也偷偷的跑到那個網上去看一下
Approximately how much time did the previous speaker spend
前面的這個演講者大概是花了多少時間
So of course I lined up 78 slides
所以我當然排了78張slides
78 slides in one
一個78張幻燈片
If each one speaks for one minute on average
如果平均每一張講一分鐘的話
I can speak for about 80 minutes
我大概會講80分鐘左右
So I hope there is still some time to take your questions
所以希望還有一些時間可以接受大家的問題
But when I speak, I tend to speak faster and faster.
那但是我講起來的時候常常會越講越快
The faster you speak, there are many things that may be unknown
越講越快有很多東西可能會語言不詳
or something unclear
或者是講的不清楚的地方
if you would like to listen a little more
如果你們願意多聽一點的話
You are welcome to interrupt me anytime
歡迎你們隨時可以打斷我
I don't need to raise my hand
我不需要舉手的
just press your microphone
只要按你的麥克風
call while i'm out of breath
在我喘氣的時候打電話
I'm willing to stop anytime
我願意隨時停下來
Let me explain a little more to you
跟大家再多做一些說明
or usually both
或者通常都是
I heard they are very polite
聽說都是非常禮貌的
according to the last
按那一道最後的
Bring it up when it's all said and done
全部都講完的時候再提起來
bring it up for discussion
提出來一起討論
that's also very welcome
那也非常歡迎
i want today
我今天要
Just like Mr. Peng said just now
就像剛才彭老師說的
I went to Tibet to go to Youshan with Wulang to play in the water
是到西藏跟烏朗去油山玩水
Playing in the oil mountains and playing in the water is actually pretty good
油山玩水其實蠻好的
This is the study of geology
這是地質學研究的
one of the few advantages
少數優點之一
I shouldn't have said that
我又不應該這麼說
one of the advantages
其中的一項優點
that I have been doing for many years
那我在過去很多年在做
One of the studies on this
這方面有關的研究之一
I'm here to tell you today
今天就來跟大家說一說
The story of the so-called geological road project
所謂地質的路計畫的故事
at the beginning
那一開始
use my old slide first
先用我的那個老slide
because of copyright issues
因為有版權的問題
That idea was planned from
那個思路計畫是從
this gentleman is here
這個先生來的
he is wal
他是華爾
He formed the so-called Music Project
他組了所謂的音樂計畫
Because of this server project
因為這個伺服計畫
They have a certain Vision
他們有一定的Vision
we think we can borrow
我們覺得可以借來
It's all about effects
都是效品一下
For this server project
以這個伺服計畫來說
For example they
譬如說他們
I hope this can create a new form of music
希望這個可以創造一種新的音樂形態來
so that he may feel he can escape
這樣他也許覺得他可以跳脫出
The family of classical music
古典音樂的那個家屬的
or related category
或者相關的範疇
We want to come here to study this idea
我們想來這個研究這個思路
do some geology research
做一些地質學的研究
Hope to make some new observations
希望可以做出一些新的觀察
Then finally the so-called
然後最後可以對這個所謂的
Noisy Mountain Collision Theory
噪山碰撞學說
some new insights
可以提出一些新的認識
Even new ideas come
甚至新的理念來
This is the Vision of our Stuff Effect
這是我們的東西效品的Vision
This thing actually happened in the past two or three years
這個東西其實就在過去兩三年來
To unlock a private project that may be the smallest for Taiwan compatriots
去解鎖一下可能台灣同胞最小的一個私立計畫
This private project is the private plan of Yongbao in 2011 by our long-term insurance expert Lin Yujie
這個私立計畫是我們的長保好手林育杰在2011年做永報私立的計畫
They spent years preparing
他們花了好多年的那個準備
spent three months on mobile
在移動花了三個月的時間
From Istanbul, Turkey
從土耳其的伊斯坦堡出發
Then run east all the way to Lanzhou in mainland China and end
然後往東一直跑到中國大陸的蘭州結束
A total of three months in the mainland within three months
一共有三個月的時間在內地三個月裡面
as long as you play tv in Chinese
只要你打電視的英文
Often see related reports
經常會看到相關的報導
They prepared for years and spent three months running him
他們準備了好幾年花了三個月來跑他
Our private program has been in existence for 17 or 18 years.
我們私立計畫已經17、18年了其實
run from Taiwan
從台灣開始跑
First ran to Southeast Asia and then gradually ran to Tibet
先跑到東南亞然後漸漸的跑到西藏
Finally started in the past six or seven years
最後在過去的六、七年開始
Further west into Iran into the elevated lock into Türkiye
更往西邊進到伊朗進到高架鎖進到土耳其
The final destination so far is to go to Istanbul
最後的終點目前為止是跑到伊斯坦堡
I am the opposite of everyone
這段我跟大家相反
16, 17, 18 years
16、17、18年的時間
Or add my previous study schedule
或者加上我前面求學的預程
The preparation process is actually
準備的過程其實是
I've been running this my whole life
我一輩子都在跑這個
run this ultra run
跑這個超級長跑
Haven't run yet
到現在為止還沒有跑完
Might as well run for a few years in the week until I
也許還可以在周跑幾年一直跑到我
you can pick me
可以選我一指
Finally in line for a year or two
最後在排隊排隊一兩年
Maybe there is still a chance to come and think about it with everyone
也許還有機會來跟大家知識一面想一下
Then I want to introduce this thing
那我要介紹這個東西
start with this
先從這個開始
I heard someone say
聽說有人說
The so-called Great Minds are discussing ideas
那個所謂的Great Minds是討論ideas
Average MindsDiscussion events
Average Minds討論events
As an old man, ask first
那作為老先問
Of course everyone doesn't like it
當然大家都不喜歡
He is Great Minds
他是Great Minds
So he is discussing ideas
所以他討論的是idea
but when he was young
但是他又年輕的時候
when he was young
他小的時候
Small minds discuss people when I was young
小的時候small minds discuss people
So if start with
所以如果先從
join this program
參加這個計畫
or me
或者我
People who do some cooperation started to introduce
做一些合作的人開始介紹起
because it's a
因為這是一個
The study that spanned many countries
跨越很多國家的那個研究
many different collaborators
很多不同的合作者
Then the middle is just the main collaborator
那這中間只是其中的主要合作者
When including the Western Himalayas, partners from mainland China are required
包括西洋喜馬拉的時候需要中國大陸的合作者
When doing Southeast Asia, Vietnam, Myanmar, India, and Malaysia are needed
做東南亞的時候需要越南、緬甸、印度、馬來西亞
There are also some collaborators who are mixed with European and American people
還有一些歐美人士混在裡面的合作者
when doing iran caucasus or turkey
做伊朗高加索或土耳其的時候
The same also needs to have some major local collaborators
同樣的也需要有當地的主要一些合作者
opposite of name filing
名字立案的對面
Of course, there is also the fellow who went to participate in Taiwan together
當然還有台灣一起去參加的那個同好
Including several people from the Institute of Earth Sciences
包括中研地球科學所的幾位
teachers and other colleges
老師還有其他的大學
Including teachers from Normal University and Chung Cheng University
包括師範大學、中正大學的老師
Finally, of course, my colleagues at National Taiwan University
最後當然還有我在台大的那個同仁們
But the most important behind-the-scenes engineering
但是其中最重要的幕後工程
Because there is no way to write a list of names here
因為沒辦法一列名字好寫在這裡
The main load is less complex than the backup load
叫主繁不及備載
Follow me if the main load is too heavy
主繁不及備載就跟我
Graduate students who have worked with me over the past ten years
在過去十多年來跟我一起工作的研究生
PhD Fellow or Research Assistant
博士會研究員或是研究助理
In fact, they played a very important role in the middle
其實他們在中間扮演了很重要的角色
So I took the opportunity of today's speech by the way
所以我利用今天演講的機會順便
A big thank you to these anonymous behind-the-scenes staff
透透的謝謝這些匿名的幕後工作人員
Before I introduce it, I may want to talk about the background of geology.
那要介紹之前我可能要講一點地質的背景
Geological background we actually do research
地質的背景我們事實上做研究
are the major mountain ranges on earth to study
是研究地球上的主要的山脈
or major noise movement
或主要的噪聲運動
The main noise movements on Earth can be divided into two broad categories
地球上的主要噪聲運動可以分成兩大類
A class called Eccretionary
一類叫做Eccretionary
Originate
Originate
aerated noise band or noise movement
或叫增氣型的噪聲帶或噪聲運動
The typical representative is Mount Annis in South America
典型的代表是南美的安利斯山
Or the words that were secretly played by the north in the past
或的以往北邊偷演的話
The Heat Engine Mountains in North America are actually similar noise belts
北美的熱機山脈其實也是類似的噪聲帶
Their main mechanism is
他們主要的機制是
Party Ocean's ocean plate facing east screen
派對洋的海洋板塊向東螢幕
Continental plates to North or South America
到北美或南美的大陸板塊
This is what is traditionally mentioned in the Plate Tectonics Society.
這家就是傳統上板塊構造學會裡面說的
screen effect
叫做螢幕作用
Continental translation is called complementarity
大陸的翻譯叫做輔充作用
Over the past ten years, we have worked with our classmates in mainland China
我們過去十多年來跟大陸的同學
Many people cooperate a lot, and now many Chinese translations have become translations of Communist bandits.
很多人合作很多 現在很多中文的翻譯都變成共匪的翻譯
I often forget what the translation for Taiwan is
常常忘記台灣的翻譯是甚麼
In addition to the Occretionary Allusion type
除了Occretionary Allusion 類型以外
In addition, there is a very important shape type called Colitional Allusion
另外還有一個很重要的造型類型叫Colitional Allusion
In Chinese, it is called collision modeling.
中文叫碰撞型的造型作用
A typical representative is the area to be introduced today
典型的代表就是今天要介紹的地區
In fact, starting from Tibet in the Himalayas in the east and going west
其實從東邊的喜馬拉雅西藏開始往西
Passing through Parnell into Iran
穿過帕尼爾進到伊朗
Then go west into the Caucasus Mountains
然後再往西進入高加索山
Inventory can be pushed all the way west to the Alps
Inventory可以一直往西推延到阿爾卑斯山
Or the four mountains on the border between France and Spain
或是法國跟西班牙交界的四山
They represent land masses from the south
它們代表的是南方來的大陸塊
The modeling movement caused by the collision with the original Eurasian continent in the north
跟北方原來的歐亞大陸產生碰撞所造成的造型運動
This shape is geologically related to my noun
這個造型在地質學上有關於我的名詞
called Pethean Allogenic Belts
叫做Pethean Allogenic Belts
Chinese called Pethean Allogenic Belts
中文叫做Pethean Allogenic Belts
There used to be an ancient ocean called the Tethys Ocean.
以前存在一個古的海洋叫特提斯洋有關係
I'll take a little time to introduce it later
我等一下會稍微花一點時間來做相關的介紹
so to discuss this
所以要討論這個東西
it is related to earth science or geology
它跟地球科學或地質學
over the past thirty to forty years
在過去三四十年來
The most important theory is called plate
最重要的一個理論叫板塊
or one of the most important theories
或最重要的理論之一
The theory of plate tectonics is related to the proposal of the English name Playtronics
板塊構造學說英文叫Playtronics的提出有關係
A doctrine or theory so far
到目前為止這樣的一個學說或理論
still in geology
仍然在地質學裡面
Or geosciences which play a certain important opinion
或地球科學裡面扮演了一定的重要的意見
I take this opportunity to introduce two famous people
我利用這個機會來介紹兩位有名的人士
When they were in the early 1970s
他們在1970年代初期的時候
This is the theory of plate tectonics
也就是板塊構造學說這個理論
when it was first proposed
剛被提出來的時候
Started research into the so-called collision between India and the Asian continent
開始進行所謂的印度跟亞洲大陸碰撞的研究
Like this is from an article they published in Science in 1975
像這是1975年他們在Science上發表的一篇文章的
the first to call the shots
第一個作主
Ugly caller now looks
很醜的作主現在看起來
but that is
但是那個是
The work result of the most Pioneer
那個最Pioneer的那個工作結果
Both gentlemen were at Masney College at the time.
這兩位先生那時候都在馬斯尼公學院
Is a young scholar at MIT
是MIT的年輕學者
Peter Mona was the assistant professor at that time
Peter Mona是那時候的assistant professor
Then Paul Taponeer was a postdoc from France
然後Paul Taponeer是從法國來的一個博士後
The two of them started a career at MIT
他們兩個在MIT開創了一份事業
Then from this in India colliding with Eurasia in Tibet
然後從這個在印度跟歐亞碰撞在西藏
A simterm was proposed in the study of Himalaya
到喜馬拉的研究裡面提出了一個simterm
called continental tectonics
叫做continental tectonics
They think continental tectonics and plate tectonics
他們認為continental tectonics跟plate tectonics
are two completely different keys
是兩個完全不同的關鍵
It turns out that the plate that student or plate tectonics
原來那個板塊那個學生或plate tectonics
It's the one from the oceanic plate
是從海洋板塊的那個那個
The theory developed in the study in the ocean
在海洋裡面的那個研究裡面所發展出來的理論
And they go on top of the continental plates
而他們到大陸板塊上面
Or it is said in the actual propaganda research in the mainland
或者在大陸的實宣研究裡面說
This study finds that it is not the same as in the ocean
這個研究發現跟海洋裡面並不結合相同
So they have to make certain corrections
所以他們要做一定的修正
For example, continental plates can produce
譬如說大陸板塊可以產生
It will produce deformation, contraction and expansion, and dragon fairy
會產生變形,會產生縮展,會產生龍仙
that's why we have such big mountains, the himalals
這是為什麼我們會有那麼大的山脈,有喜馬拉爾山
Then there is such a big plateau behind, Jinzang Plateau Longqi
然後後面有那麼大的高原,金藏高原龍起
So this whole becomes the infinite situation of today's world
所以這整個變成今天的世界的無極的情況
Then over the past ten years of research here
然後在過去十多年來的研究在這裡
In particular, the continental crust here
特別的表現出來,這裡的大陸地殼
or the entire continental lithosphere, continental plates
或者是整個大陸岩石圈,大陸板塊
Will it cause severe deformation?
是不是會產生強烈變形呢?
with oceanic plates, or the traditional Play Deconics concept
跟海洋板塊,或傳統的Play Deconics的觀念
is completely different, so they think
是完全不一樣,所以他們認為
There is a new bucket face that needs to be studied in more detail
有一個新的斗面需要做更詳細的研究
Then the next thing I will do later will be related to the French relationship behind this
那我待會接下來的東西會跟這個後面的法國關係
We have many, many wonderful entanglements with him now
我們現在跟他有很多很多很奇妙的糾葛在裡面
Then if you watch Play Deconics
那如果看Play Deconics的話
this is one, could be one
這個是一個,可能是一個
New Models of America, Play Deconics, Play Boundaries
美國的新的模式,Play Deconics,Play Boundaries
There are about 50 large and small plates on the surface of the earth
這個地球表面上大概有50個大大小小的板塊
do mutual exercise each other squeeze each other
互相做相互運動互相擠互相
呃呃interaction
呃呃interaction
then we will introduce
那我們要介紹
It's the little piece in the picture.
就是這個圖裡面的小小的這一塊
all
所有的
Well
呃
my thinking plan
我的思路計畫
if you
如果你
If you don't recognize this place
認不到這個地方來的話
In fact, this place is mainly two
其實這個地方主要是兩個
Well
呃
Continental to Continental Collision
大陸跟大陸的那個碰撞
the one created by the orogen
造山所造出來的那個
uh mountains
呃山脈
is currently on Earth
是目前地球上
most important
最重要
or the most
或是最
uh uh
呃呃
conspicuous two colliding wars
顯眼的兩個碰撞的戰爭
one is here
一個是在這裡
yes this is tibet
是這裡是西藏
Or with the mountains around Tibet
或者跟西藏周邊的山
linked together
連結在一起
To the north is Space Mountain.
北邊是空間山這邊
There is also Carat Space, to the south is the Himalayas
還有克拉空間南邊是喜馬拉雅山
etc.
等等
together this
合在一起這個
I call it the Tibetan Himalayan War for short.
就我叫簡稱它叫西藏喜馬拉雅戰爭
it is mainly
它主要是
This section should be ruled
應律這個板塊
reciprocal motion to the north
向北邊做相互運動
Hitting the Eurasian road plate
撞到歐亞道路板塊
The result of this place
這個地方所造出來的結果
What about its west side?
那另外它的西邊呢
There's another Collision War zone
有另外一個碰撞戰爭帶
it is the arabic plate
它是阿拉伯這塊板塊
I bought most of them in Asia, and this place was made
我亞大都買,這個地方造出來
These two states, if we use a little bit
這兩個狀態,如果我們用個點點點
It is a map projected from major earthquakes
是比較主要地震投影出來的圖
Or if the earthquake takes it away
或者是如果地震拿掉的話
You can see that this color can actually come out
你看這個顏色其實可以出來
These two are to the east or west of Asia
這兩個在亞洲的東邊或西邊
I call it the East Asian collision zone for short.
我簡稱它叫東亞的碰撞帶人類
Collision with Western Asia Brings Humans
跟西亞的碰撞帶人造成類
The most obvious difference is that this one is fatter
最明顯的差別是這個比較胖
this is thinner
這個是比較瘦
same principle
跟原理一樣
I used to be slim
我以前是比較苗條的
But now it has become more and more like Mr. Peng
但是現在已經變得越來越像彭老師了
I'm physically
我在身材上
so
所以
This compares
這比較
Compare
比較
Immense
Immense
then this
然後這個
this
這個
narrow
狹窄
The time with which this crime took place
跟這個造案帶發生的時間
There are relationships
有關係
We call this collision zone a relatively mature collision zone.
這個碰撞帶我們叫做是比較成熟的碰撞帶
because it started earlier
因為它開始的時間比較早
In geological history, probably
在地質的歷史裡面大概是
60 million years
60個百萬年
That is, around 60 million years ago
也就是6千萬年左右開始
India and Asia collide
印度跟亞洲開始碰撞
This collision zone is a younger collision zone
這碰撞帶是比較年輕的碰撞帶
it happened earlier
它發生的時間比較早
This time may be about 30 million years in the average concensus
這個時間可能在大約一般的concensus大概是30個百萬年
It started only about 30 million years ago
就是3000萬年左右才開始
So half younger than this
所以比這個年輕的一半
so this young
所以這個年輕
And at the same time, it has a lot to do with the speed and intensity of the picture drama that collides with the plate
而且同時跟碰撞板塊的繪劇的速度跟激烈程度有很大的關係
Hardness runs fast
硬度跑得很快
arabian run very slow
阿拉伯跑得很慢
So if we look at this simple cartoon
所以如果我們用這個簡單的卡通圖來看的話
The one who loves to learn will
愛學的一個將會
Diton Wheeler is made by Germans
Diton Wheeler就是德國人做
The digital picture drawn by the education plate reconstruction
教育做板塊重建畫出來的digital的那個圖
but I simply treat it as
但是我簡單把它當作
You can see that the original hardness lags behind
你看原來的時候硬度落在後面
Then anytime progress hardness ran to the front
然後隨時進展硬度跑到前面來了
So hard like an Indian cheetah
所以硬度就像一個Indian cheetah
the animal that runs as fast as a tough cheetah
像硬度的獵豹一樣跑得很快的那個動物
Then the Arabic plate
然後阿拉伯板塊的
In fact, they are all glued to this huge flying boat plate.
其實都黏在這個很龐大的飛舟板塊上面
So the airship is like a bubbun
所以飛舟就像一個bubbun像一樣
It is lined up from the Southern Continent Pioneer
它是從南方大陸先鋒列開來
but it runs very slowly
但是它跑得很慢
move slowly north
緩慢的往北邊做移動
India's departure time is relatively late
印度開始出發的時間是比較晚
But it's last come first come fast
但是它後發先至用很快的速度
Run to the north and south and then first load to the edge of Eurasia
跑到北邊南然後先裝到歐亞大陸邊緣
So here we build mountains first
所以這邊先造山
On the contrary, the mountain formation was late
這邊反而晚造山
It's more intense here
這邊碰到的比較激烈
because india runs fast
因為印度跑得很快
So here's the orogenic India
所以這裡的造山印度
You're doing more than what's being done here
你進行的要比這邊的造成來得厲害
right
對
This is the case of General
這是General的那個情況
If you push back the history of the earth
如果你把地球的歷史再往前去推
longer words
更長的時間的話
It's just the schematic diagram of that and that.
就是剛才那個那個那個的示意圖
This is India is Africa
這裡是印度就是非洲
Then India quickly ran up
然後印度很快的跑上來
Africa is connected to the Arabian
非洲連著這個它最東北邊的阿拉伯
run slowly
慢慢的往前跑
But this is in the history of the address
但是這個是在地址的歷史裡面的
One hundred and twenty ninety million years
百二季九十個百萬年
Then if you push forward
然後你如果再往前推的話
one hundred and seventy million years
一百七十個百萬年
two hundred and forty million years
兩百四十個百萬年
three hundred million years three hundred and forty
三百百萬年三百四十
Until five hundred and forty centuries
一直到五百四十個百年
Five hundred and forty centuries
五百四十個百年
Probably the beginning of the cold afternoon season in address history
大概是地址歷史的寒午季的開始
That is the beginning of the fifth generation
也就是五生代的開始
The words before there are
在那邊之前的話就是
Is it the pre-cold noon season?
是不是要前寒午季
nice to fly
很好飛
in a different history
在不同的歷史裡面
You can see that the combination of the plates will change
你看到板塊是會的組合是會變動的
there will be one after another
會有紛紛合合
We specially put this picture about 24 million years old for you to see
我們特別把這個兩百四百萬年左右的圖放到給你看
The topic I'm going to cover today is about
我今天要介紹的主題有關
At this time there was a big ancient ocean
這個時候有一個很大的古的海洋
This ancient marine geologist gave him a special name called the Tethys Ocean
這個古的海洋地質學家給他一個特別名叫做特提斯洋
English called Tesla Ocean
英文叫Tesla Ocean
Chinese translation
中文的翻譯
Ogain is the translation of the big country called Tethys
Ogain是大國的翻譯叫特提斯
Taiwan's translation is called ancient Mediterranean
台灣的翻譯叫做古地中海
if you have heard
如果你有聽過的話
But Tethys is actually a very bad translation
但是特提斯其實是一個很不好的翻譯
because it sounds hard
因為聽起來很難聽話
But Tethysthetis was actually a water god
但是特提斯特提斯其實是一個水神
Or Poseidon is a goddess of female beauty
或者海神是一個女性漂亮的女神
Translating Tethys can't show it at all
翻譯特提斯一點都沒辦法展現出來
So I secretly translated it into Daixis last time
所以我上個時候都偷偷的把它翻成叫代西斯
That sounds like the name of a goddess
這樣聽起來就是女神的名字
At this time, the combination of Tethys Yang looks like this
在這個時候特提斯洋的組合大概是這樣子
Tethys ocean geologists go further
特提斯洋地質學家更進一步分的話
It can be divided into what is called Pilotastic called ancient
可以把它分成叫做Pilotastic叫古
Mesotasis is called Mesotasis
Mesotasis 叫中特迪士
Called New Tedis sheep with Neotasis
跟Neotasis 叫新特迪士羊
So there's a lot of subtle changes in between
所以這中間有很多細微的變化
Then wait until the Paleozoic to Mesozoic period of this Earth's history
然後等到從這個地球歷史的古生代到中生代
Until the end of the whole evolution of the new generation
一直到新生代這個整個演化結束了以後
Continents from the south make relative applications to the north
南方來的大陸 往北邊做相對應用
Finally close up this teddy sheep
最後把這個特迪士羊關閉起來
we get what we see today
我們就得到今天我們看到的
The so-called error status band
所謂的失誤的狀態帶
From Tibet, Himalayas, Europa to
從西藏 喜馬賴亞 歐羅的衛一直到
Albert in the west, the Perakins, etc.
西邊的阿爾貝 霹靂牛斯山等等
Proper nouns in cartography
在地圖學上的專有名詞
In fact, it should be called Tephanogene belt
其實應該是叫它做Tephanogene belt
It's the Teddis War Belt I mentioned earlier.
就是我前面提到的特迪士 造戰帶
It is about taking this ancient Mediterranean
它講的就是把這個古的地中海
or after this teddy sheep is closed
或這個特迪士羊關閉了以後
continental plates from the south
南方來的大陸的板塊
To the north is mainly the Eurasian continental plate
跟北方的主要是歐亞大陸板塊
when the main things come together
為主的東西合在一起的時候
the result of
所造出來的結果
So my Chinese Academy of Sciences in Beijing
所以我的北京中國科學院
Wu Furen
地圖所的同仁吳復仁
It's called they are also working on a joint project
叫做他們同時也在做合作計畫
The name of their joint project will be
他們的合作計畫的名字就有了
It's officially called the Tres project
很正規叫做特級斯計畫
everybody knows
大家都知道
The president's committee and geologists all know
總統委是地質學家都知道
But because my project is in Taiwan
但是因為我的計畫是在台灣
Then interdisciplinary students have to follow physical chemistry
然後是跨學們要跟物理化學
Mathematics students compete together
數學的學們一起來競爭的
So it is necessary to take a comparison
所以必須要取一個比較
Compare
比較
relatively unpronounceable name
比較不能夠拗口的名字
So it becomes a four-way plan
所以就變成四路計畫
The Tres plan is a very complicated thing.
那特級斯計畫就很複雜的東西
i don't say it in particular
我不特別去說它
but must stand
但是必須站在
Also very important in geology
在地質學的也非常重要的
The effect of the global global factor
全球性的 global factor 的效應
global impact
對全球的衝擊
not just on the road
不只是在路上
You can easily understand on the road
路上你很容易了解
because the board will hit
因為板會碰到
then there are mountains formed
然後有山脈形成
So the authenticity on the watch is different
所以不表上的地道不一樣
when there is such a big plateau
當有那麼大的高原
when it melts
融起的時候
Obviously the road will be affected
顯然路上是要受影響的
But the impact isn't just on the road
但這個影響不只是在路上
while in the sea
同時在海裡面
with the air
跟空氣
Air is the change in the atmosphere
空氣是大氣圈裡面的變化
There are also very
也有很
have a serious impact
產生很嚴重的衝擊
like in terms of the ocean
像以海洋來說的話
Because of the movement of India to Arabia and North
因為印度跟阿拉伯本和北的移動
Then the ancient Mediterranean will be specially closed
然後把古的地中海會特地關閉起來
It turns out that the currents of the Atlantic Ocean and the Indian Ocean South
原來大西洋的洋流跟印度洋南
The currents of the Pacific Ocean are interconnected
是太平洋的洋流是可以互通的
Wait until this channel is closed
等到這個通道被關起來以後
Wait until Arabia would have crashed into Eurasia
等到阿拉伯本會撞上歐亞大陸以後
This channel is closed
這個通道就被關閉了
After closing, you can easily think of
關閉以後你很容易聯想到
Global ocean currents are greatly affected and will change
全球的洋流受到很巨大的影響會改變
So this closing time
所以這個關閉的時間
Probably in the history of the earth
大概在地球歷史裡面
The 30 million years I mentioned earlier
剛才我提到的這個30個百萬年
about 30 million years
大概3000萬年左右
30 million years in the history of the earth
3000萬年那個地球歷史裡面的時間
Oligocene is called gradually new type
叫Oligocene叫做漸新式
So when oscillating
所以在漸新式的時候
In the evolution of earth history
在地球歷史演變裡面
The event with a global cooling
有一個全球的cooling的那個事件
As far as many scholars have begun to discuss
就很多學者就開始去討論說
Is it because of this change in ocean currents?
是不是因為這個洋流的改變
or the closure of this pipe
或這個管道的封閉
Is there any connection with the global goblin cooling?
跟全球的goblin cooling有沒有一定的關聯
Many related research associations
很多相關的研究會
If changes to the global climate
如果影響到全球氣候的變化
This is the impact on the air
這就是對空的衝擊
Effects are not limited to changes on land or on the ground
影響不只是影響到陸地上或地面的改變
In fact, in the ocean
其實對海洋裡面
or atmospheric wind twist
或者是大氣的風扭
will have a serious impact
都會產生很嚴重的衝擊
in these fields
在這些領域裡面
Many related scholars are doing relevant research
都有很多相關的學者在做相關的研究
Then I will post a few more slides to talk about it
那我再發幾張slide來說一下
what is my beijing friend
什麼是我的北京的朋友
no woman ready slide
無婦人準備的slide
So it's all simplified characters
所以都是簡體字
So what is a special editor?
那什麼是特輯師呢
The special editor simply said that the earth
特輯師就是簡單地說地球
There was an ancient ocean in between
中間存在過一個古海洋
ancient ocean
古的海洋
we call
我們叫
not us
不是我們
This is the first person to call him
這個是最早叫他的人
is a supplementary student in Austria
是奧地利的一個補充學生
Named Tessis in 1893 called Swiss
叫Swiss的1893年命名的名叫Tessis
Tessis is the beautiful lady
Tessis是這位漂亮的那個小姐
Or he is Seafood Oceanus
或者是他是海鮮 Oceanus的
So it should be translated into a more feminine name
所以應該要翻譯成比較女性化一點的名字
maybe less obtrusive
可能比較不會那麼突兀
So this is the Curtis Ocean in Earth's past history
所以這是克蒂斯洋在地球過去的歷史裡面
The southern hemisphere is not between the southern continent and the northern continent
南半球不是南方的大陸跟北方的大陸之間
an ancient ocean that once existed
曾經存在的一個古海洋
In the middle because this ancient ocean is now extinct
那中間因為這個古海洋現在已經消滅了
So do not keep records that are no longer kept
所以不保持不再保留的記錄
or a record kept in the address history
或者是在地址歷史裡面保持的記錄
are incomplete
都是不完全的
So there are many, many different arguments or different scholars
所以有很多很多不同的爭論或不同的學者
offer different explanations
提出不同的解釋
Like one of the scholars who wrote an article
像其中就有一位學者寫了一篇文章
Specifically to take advantage of the difference in the spelling of Curtis's name
專門來利用克蒂斯的名字的拼法的那個差異來說
In fact, there are many, many different debates in it
其實有很多很多不同的debates在裡面
How should Curtis be composed?
克蒂斯該是怎麼組成
Then the time of his formation
然後他的形成的時間
where does he exist
他是在哪裡存在
How did he evolve
然後他是怎麼演化的
have many different interpretations
都有很多不同的解釋
Or even more naughty is a Turkish geoscientist named Chera Sengo
或者有更調皮的是一個土耳其的地球學家叫Chera Sengo
His dedicated article discusses
他專門寫的文章討論
Teddy's story
特迪斯的故事
Then Punchline is
然後Punchline是
How many wives did oceanists have?
How many wives did oceanists have?
How many wives do oceanists have?
到底 oceanists有多少個太太?
If you want to know a little more about Teddy Yang's story
你如果想知道多一點的關於特迪斯洋的故事的話
i always recommend
我總建議
my student
我的學生
but you are not my students
但你們不是我的學生
then i will talk about shanko
然後我再談談善科說
Say a lot to use that wiki site
說多多利用那個維基網站
Wikipedia actually has a lot of related information
Wikipedia上面其實有很多相關的資訊
So you just hit Testis Ocean
所以你就只要打Testis Ocean
You can find a lot of related information on Wikipedia
在Wikipedia上可以搜尋到很多相關的資訊
Then I'll make this Teddys case tape.
那我來做這個特迪斯造案帶
or do this idea
或者做這個思路計畫
There are so many complex geological problems
有那麼多複雜的地質問題
of course do everything
當然每一項都做
Then my reasoning for that research
那我對那個研究的理應
Like the introduction of Punchline just now
像剛才Punchline介紹
Geochemistry of mainly igneous rocks
主要是火冰岩的地球化學
So holding hands to two is
所以牽手到兩個是
The first is geochemical
第一個是地球化學
Geochemistry means
地球化學的意思就是
We use chemical knowledge or technology to study
我們用化學的知識或技術來研究
Earth Today or Study Earth's History
今天地球或研究地球的歷史
So using chemical
所以利用化學的
Our Tongren Association Academia Sinica at National Taiwan University
我們在台大的同仁會中研院
There are many sessions dedicated to geophysics
有很多是地球物理的專場
They use their knowledge of physics
他們就利用物理的知識
or physical techniques to study the earth
或物理的技術來研究地球
eventually modern earth science is hope
eventually 摩登的地球科學就是希望
All the knowledge and technology at our disposal
所有我們可以利用到的那個知識跟技術
Come to study and do modern earth science research
來研究做現代的那個地球科學研究
So we claim to be modern geoscientists
所以我們號稱是摩登地球科學家
I thought the former students were sitting in the back when I said that
我說的時候我以為以前的學生坐在後面
Or my students don't quite believe
或者我的學生都不太相信
i am a modern earth
我是一個摩登的地球
chemist or modern geoscientist
化學家或摩登的地球科學家
Because I still don't know how to use a mobile phone
因為我到現在還不會用手機
because it's geochemistry
因為這是地球化學
The other one is igneous rock
另外一個是火塵岩
Fire dust rock means
火塵岩的意思就是
molten rock uses rocks formed in volcanoes or magma
融融的岩石會用火山中或岩漿中形成的岩石
This is my research session
這是我的研究專場
so in this area
所以在這個地區
In the history of Alu Collision Stitching
在阿路碰撞縫合的歷史中
lots of magmatism
有很多岩漿作用
Many rock records of igneous rocks have been left
留下了很多火塵岩的岩石紀錄
So we're here to study
所以我們就在這個地方來研究
This magmatism
這個岩漿作用
leave a record and then study his chronology
留下的紀錄 然後去研究他的年代學
when was it formed
是什麼時候形成的
study his origins
研究他的原始學
What are his primitive characteristics?
他的原始學特徵是什麼樣的
what kind of stone is it made of
是哪一種石頭組成的
and then study the composition of his geochemistry
然後研究他的地球化學的成分
and then combine these
然後綜合這些
What about the records of Yanjiang's homework?
研疆作業的紀錄呢
he will tell us something
他會告訴我們一些
this
這個
collision history or creation
碰撞歷史或造生
some records in the process
過程中的一些紀錄
Then this kind of research needs a basic assumption
那這樣子研究需要一個基本的假設
The assumption is that
這個假設就是
There is a certain relationship between the research and Xinjiang activities and the so-called plate tectonic work
研疆活動跟所謂的板塊構造作業有一定的那個關聯
When the plate tectonic environment changes
當板塊構造環境改變的時候
Yanjiang
他如果造成研疆
If it is produced to research the ingredients of Xinjiang
如果造出來研疆的成分
or his primordial character
或者他的原始學特性
will follow
會跟
Under different plate tectonic environments before
之前的不同板塊構造環境之下
The composition of a Yanjiang produced is different
造出來的一個研疆的成分是不一樣的
for example
譬如說
The research frontier formed before the collision between India and Asia
在這個印度跟亞洲碰撞之前形成的研疆
India and Asia
印度跟亞洲
Yanjiang formed after the collision
碰撞之後形成的研疆
it will have a very different documented nature
它會有截然不同的紀錄化性質
We just need to know when he made this change
我們只要知道他在什麼時候產生這個變化
he'll tell us
他就會告訴我們說
how did this collision happen
這個碰撞是怎麼產生的
what happened in this process
這樣過程中發生了哪一些
we look fun
我們看起來很有趣的
Wait a minute and I'll give you a few examples
等一下我會舉幾個例子給大家看
such a hypothesis
這樣的一個假設
We have done a lot of work in Tibet
我們在西藏上做了不少的工作
Tibet is from an article I published in 2015
西藏這是我2015年發表的一個文章裡面的
The first graph, the first extreme simplification
第一個圖 第一個極端簡化的
Address map of Tibet
西藏的地址圖
I tell you this is the time to oversimplify
我跟你們講說這是極端簡化的時候
Everyone smiled incomprehensibly
大家都露出不可理解的微笑
or some kind of smile
或者是某一種的笑容
But this is indeed an extremely simplified address map
但這個的確是極端簡化的地址圖
I can explain to you well because of this time
我因為這個時間可以好好地跟你們解釋
Divide the whole Tibet into one, two, three, four, five, six
把整個西藏分成一二三四五六
Seven kinds of stones are posted on this picture
七種石頭就發在這個圖上
you really have a chance to see
你真的有機會去看看
The address on the Tibetan Plateau
西藏高原地址上面
Densely packed with dozens of rocks of different ages
密密麻麻的有幾十種不同時代的岩石
or stratum
或者是地層
Twice very very tutoring
兩次非常非常輔導
This is an extremely simplified spectrum
這個是極端簡化的譜
Then use such an extremely simplified synthesis
然後利用這樣的極端簡化的synthesis
We can then discuss what the tectonic evolution of the Tibetan Plateau looks like
我們就可以討論西藏高原的構造演化大概是什麼樣子
If you are interested, please take a look
那如果你有興趣可以請看看
But it is not suitable for me to talk too much about that old stuff
但是我今天不適合講太多那個太學舊的那個東西
But this article is quite resonant
但是這個文章其實蠻反響
We spent a lot of time doing this
我們花了不少時間來做這件事
Published in a geological neutralization period called erscience review
發表在一個地質學的那個中和期間叫erscience review上
science review has a statistic in 2010
science review在2010年有一個統計
We got a good citation for this article
我們這個文章得到很好的那個citation
It is the paper defined by the ranking in all the highly cited papers
是所有那個highly cited paper裡面排名定義的那個paper
So it's still useful to draw some effort
所以表示畫一番功夫還是有用的
Then do something like this
那要做這樣的那個東西
As I said just now, my research is called
就像我剛才說的要我這個研究是所謂的
modern digital art learning English is really modern
modern digital art學英文真的modern
That is closely related to the development of that instrument and technology.
那跟那個仪器跟技術的那個發展有很密切的關係
Let me briefly talk about some kind of technical chemical development
那我這邊簡單的說某種技術化學發展
with the technological development of so-called spectrometers
跟所謂的質普儀的技術發展
Mass spectrometer is mass spectrometer
質普儀是 mass spectrometer
Now we technical chemists use many kinds of spectrometers
那我們現在技術化學家用很多各式各樣的那個質普儀
to do the measurement we want
來做我們想做的那個測量
That way that precise measurement
那這樣子那個精密的測量
We call it prime number
我們叫它做質普數
It is mass spectrometry
就是 mass spectrometry
For example, the element we need
那譬如說我們需要的那個元素
or isotopic measurement
或者同位式的測量
We just try to find a way in the periodic table
我們就想辦法在周期表裡面
find our suitable element or isotope
找到我們合適的那個元素或同位素
Then use mass spectrometry to do accurate
然後利用質普儀來做精確的
or that precise measurement at very low levels
或者是非常低含量的那個精確測量
can achieve what we want
可以達到我們所要的那個目的
The technological development of this kind is about the same as that of the past ten years
那這樣的那個技術發展跟過去大概十年來
To some extent, the Department of Geology at National Taiwan University is similar to the so-called
在台大地質系某種程度也跟所謂的
The knowledge plan of 50 billion in five years has a lot to do with it
五年五百億的那個知識計畫有很大的關聯
So 50 billion in five years is actually
所以五年五百億其實
Actually did a lot of good things
其實也做了不少好事
at least in row
至少在排大
We took this opportunity to set up a couple of really nice labs
我們利用這個機會建立幾個很不錯的實驗室
In the past few years, I have made a lot of new observations and new bags
在過去的幾年做了不少的新的觀察跟新的包包
Including some research results in the thinking plan that I will introduce to you later
包括我待會要跟各位介紹的思路計畫裡面的一些研究成果
The front is all introduction
那前面全部是introduction
To see this, to talk about my thoughts and plans
要看這件要講我的思路計畫
Since it is an imitation
既然是模仿
Youyou Music Ideas Project
有有的音樂思路計畫
So I will divide it into about three components to introduce to you
所以我就把它分成大概三個components來跟大家做介紹
divided into preludes
分為前奏曲
then enter the topic
然後進入到主題
then finally to the finale
然後最後到終曲
The prelude will probably be divided into two parts
前奏曲大概會分成兩部分
The topic will be divided into two parts
主題會分成兩部分
One is a good place in the Tibetan Himalayas in the east
一個是東邊的西藏喜馬拉好地方
then one is tibet
然後一個是西藏
To the west are the two regions from the Caucasus to Iran
西邊的是高加索到伊朗這兩個地區
It is related to a very strange research project in China.
前面就有一個國內很奇怪的研究計畫有關係
This research project was developed by us 17 or 18 years ago
這個研究計畫是我們在17、18年前
Starting to leave Taiwan and go to Southeast Asia to do geological science research
開始要離開台灣到東南亞去做地質科學的研究說
A topic I thought up with my feet in my head
想腳進腦汁想出來的一個題目
So our research project is called CREATE
所以我們的研究計畫叫CREATE
Tainan Chinese is simply called the East Asian Terran Tectonic Research Integration Project
台南中文很簡單叫東亞地體構造研究整合計畫
English name is Comprehensive Research on East Asia Tectonic Evolution
英文叫Comprehensive Research on East Asia Tectonic Evolution
Become a Synchron name called CREATE
變成一個Synchron name叫CREATE
We hope this will convince the review committee of the State Council
我們希望這樣子可以說服國務會的評審委員
Give us a little more funding for research
多給我們一點研究的經費
We can go to places outside of Taiwan to work hard and see
我們可以去台灣外面的地方打拼打拼看看
On the one hand, self-encouragement hopes that we can create some new observations or theories to
一方面自我鼓勵希望我們可以創出一些新的觀察或理論來
This research project is now part of the Ninth Science Division of Congress
這個研究計畫現在變成國會會第九科學學門裡面
It was a very successful plan
算是很成功的一個計畫
Because it has lasted for sixteen seventeen years and has not been terminated
因為已經延續了十六十七年還沒有被terminate掉
Seventeen years is about three years we have been together
十七年就是我們大概三年一起
It is now in the sixth period
現在已經做進行到第六期
Three sixty-eight will have a total of eighteen years of planning
三六十八一共會有十八年的計畫
Now in middle second year of sixth period
現在在第六期的中間第二年
So now I'm doing the research project for the 17th year
所以現在正來做第十七年的那個研究計畫
Hosley, we can still maintain a certain creativity
Hosley我們還可以保持一定的creativity
Do a few more years of related work in the next few years
在未來幾年再多做幾年相關的工作
What about the create research project?
那create研究計畫呢
The first place to start is in Southeast Asia
出發的第一個地方在東南亞
Mount Ai Lao on the Red River in Vietnam
在越南的紅河艾勞山
In Vietnam part is actually the Red River
在越南部分其實是紅河
If anyone has ever been to North Vietnam
如果有人去過北越王過的話
Going northwest from Hanoi
從河內往西北邊走
you will see a big river
你會看到一條很大河
That river is the Red River
那個河就是紅河
The Red River is actually a very big break
紅河其實是一個非常大的斷交
or fault zone
或者叫做斷裂帶
So the reason why I chose to start solving the problem here
所以會選在這裡開始破題的原因
We were originally studying the formation of the South China Sea
是我們原來在研究南海的形成
There is a theory about the formation of the South China Sea
南海的形成有其中有一個理論說
It has something to do with the activity of this big fault zone.
跟這個大的斷裂帶活動有關係
Its range is about 1000 kilometers long
它的範圍大概是1000公里長的範圍
is a big fault
是一個很大的斷層
lasted 1000 km
延續了1000公里
So a fault about three times as long as Taiwan
所以大概是台灣的三倍長的一個斷層
so do it here
所以在這邊做
It is completely different from the scale in Taiwan.
就是跟台灣的scale是完全不一樣的
Why this big break
為什麼這個大的斷裂
Or why you want to do research on this large fault zone
或者為什麼想來做這個大斷裂帶的相關研究
It's related to the job of the gentleman I mentioned earlier named Taboneer
跟我前面提到的那位先生叫Taboneer的工作有關係
Taboneer with some colleagues or students at the University of Paris
Taboneer跟巴黎大學的一些同事或學生
Started publishing successive research papers in 1986
在1986年開始發表陸續的研究論文
Let's talk about this fault zone
來討論這個斷裂帶
The importance of this fault zone is
這個斷裂帶的重要性在
They think that after India collided with Asia
他們認為說印度跟亞洲碰撞了以後
In addition to causing the hearing impairment
一共除了造成那個聽障
The amphibious continental extortion caused by the dragon body on the Tibetan plateau in East Asia
西藏高原的龍身以外在東亞造成兩棲的continental extortion
Experiments of the mainland's descent or complementation
大陸的脫裔或脫補的試驗
like pool
就像撞球一樣
You hit it and two balls go out
你打了一下有兩個球跑出去
Then two boards ran out
然後有兩個板子跑出去
After sports hit
運動撞進來以後
The southeast pottery that first formed the Southeast Asian plate
先造成東南亞板塊的向東南陶藝
Then cause the Tibetan plateau plus the relative motion of eastern Asia to the east
然後再造成西藏高原加上亞洲東部向東的相對運動
The boundary between the first period and the second period is the Red River Erosendian era
第一期跟第二期轉換的邊界就是紅河埃羅森代年代
model is very famous
模型非常有名
Until now
到現在為止
in all geology
在所有的地質學裡面
Textbooks of structural geology have this picture
構造地質的教科書裡面都有這個圖
This is like a model of some kind
這等於是一個某種的典範一樣
or an authoritative explanation
或者是一個權威式的解釋
Even because of this work and the NSF in mainland China
甚至因為這個工作跟中國大陸的NSF
Their foundation committee declared that
他們的基金委宣稱說
The problems of this place have been solved by him
這個地方的問題都被他解決了
So any mainland China study
所以任何中國大陸研究
Apply to study all of the research topics in this place
申請研究這個地方的研究課題都
kill them all
都把他們殺掉
because there is no problem to do
因為沒有問題可以做了
about 15 years ago
大概在15年以前
When we set off in Taiwan to discuss
我們在台灣出發要討論的時候
We thought this pattern was really beautiful
我們就覺得這個模式實在是太漂亮了
so beautiful let us think
太漂亮讓我們想到
that word is called
那個話叫做
To be true
To be true
we just want to try it
我們就想去試試看
The national tiger who was not born with the poison of France
那個出生之毒不為法國的國虎
I want to come here to challenge
想來這邊挑戰挑戰
have a look
看看
Just choose this place to make our first step
就選在這個地方做我們的第一步
Although there are certain risks
雖然有一定的風險但是
feel like playing
覺得玩起來
may be more enjoyable
可能比較過癮
When I went to Huashan, I met many
去了華山就碰到很多
Study on the Ho Chi Minh Trail
在胡志明小徑上就研究
not so easy
沒有那麼容易
That's a small thing except the cable car
那除了這個線車是小事
but we
但是我們
good luck
運氣蠻好的
found in the previous 12 years
在前面的1 2年找到的
Several very important geological roads
好幾個很重要的地質路頭
then quickly do some
然後很快的做一些
analyze
分析
In 1997 and 1998 respectively in
在1997年跟1998年分別在
The mainstream period of the Georgia Society of America
美國地質學會Georgia Society of America的主流期
Called Georgia published two papers on the Red River Alasan fault zone
叫Georgia上面發表了兩篇關於紅河阿拉桑斷裂帶的論文
That view is completely different from that of the French gang.
那個觀點跟法國幫的那個觀點完全不一樣
So there was an uproar
所以引起了軒然大波
From then on, the French hated the things that Tuantuan made very much.
從此以後法國人非常討厭那個團團做的東西
The incomprehensible resources we have forged with him have continued to this day
我們跟他結下的不解資源一直到現在為止
I always tell people that this is an incomprehensible fate
我都跟人家說這是不解的孽緣
Tarponia still hates our team so much
現在為止塔波尼亞還非常討厭我們的那個團隊
because some of the things we published
因為我們發表的一些東西
I think there are many in the model that he was very beautiful at the time
覺得他當初非常漂亮的那個模型裡面有很多
The problem with Fundamental
Fundamental的那個問題
In fact, it should be the wrong foothold.
其實應該是那個立足點就就是錯了
So until now I'm still fighting
所以一直到現在為止還在繼續在做吵架
But for me personally, the research on the Red River Alashan fault zone is more important
但是對我個人來說其實那個紅河阿拉桑斷裂帶的研究更重要的是
Track to the northwest by tracking the Red River Alashan
利用追蹤紅河阿拉桑往西北方追蹤
This is where the Red River Alashan breaks
這是紅河阿拉桑斷裂的
In the end we climbed up the Qinghai-Tibet Plateau
結果我們爬上了慶藏高原
So I went to the Qinghai-Tibet Plateau and made some things
所以到慶藏高原上面做了一些東西
Also sent a paper that looks good
還發了一個看起來不錯的那個paper
But more importantly, after this prelude
但是更重要的是從這個前奏曲以後
One of the topics we can remember to cover today
我們可以記住到今天要介紹的那個主題之一
It is the create project and Tibet research
就是create計畫跟西藏研究
That went to the infinite of this world
那上了這個世界的無極
It's easy to think of words of encouragement
很容易想一些鼓勵自己的話嘛
Quickly copy a sentence out
趕快抄一句出來
Everyone felt inspired and went to Tibet
大家覺得受到鼓舞就上西藏去了
Up Zufan
上去的祖凡 複集貝德
So I like to use this composite picture to say that so many people went
所以我喜歡用這張綜合圖說有那麼多人去了
The people in the colorful photos are our working team
彩色的照片裡面的人都是我們工作的團隊
Except this black and white
除了這張黑白的
That's the other picture you saw on the poster
也就是你們在海報上看到的另一張相
This was when I was in Tibet about ten years ago
這是我大概十年前在西藏的時候
My graduate student at that time helped me take the photo
我那個時候的研究生幫我拍的
Intentionally shot in black and white
故意還拍成黑白的
It looks particularly memorable now
現在看起來特別值得回味的樣子
Looks like the one from Fuji
看起來就像因為富籍的那個
The young man with a big bag on his back went to Tibet to learn Buddhist scriptures
背了一個大包包的那個年輕人到西藏去取經
explore that
探索那個
is the secret of an address
是一張地址的秘訣
When the boss was chatting
這個老闆當時聊天的時候
He's 84 and it's been 10 years
他是84歲已經過了10年了
Now if he is still there
現在他如果還在的話
hope he's still there
希望他還在
and in good
而且在很好
is 94 years old
就是94歲
He looked very, very healthy at the time
那個時候看起來他非常非常的健康
their next world
他們的下個世上
this one
就這個
It was only after the whole set was given to me that I found out
就整體這個套給我才發現
In fact, that Bradbitt has been working on that private road project for a long time.
其實那個布萊德比特早就在做那個私路計畫
run far ahead of me
遠遠跑在我的前面
Brad Beatt acted in a Hollywood movie when he was young
布萊德比特年輕的時候演的一個好萊塢的電影
Called 7 Years in Tibet
叫做7 Years in Tibet
Many people may have seen
很多人可能都看過
It's about a late World War II
講的是一個那個二次大戰晚期
The story of an Austrian mountaineer named Hirish Barrow
一個奧地利的登山學家叫Hirish Barrow的那個故事
Last time I was stuck in my heart for 7 years
上次被困在心上待了7年
And also met Dalai Nana
而且還認識了達賴娜娜
Dalai Nana's childhood story
達賴娜娜小的時候的故事
If you haven't seen it, go and have a look
你沒有看過的話趕快去找來看一看
Why do you say he is already working on a private road project?
為什麼說他已經在做私路計畫
You'll be fucking Brad Pitt later
等一下你還會幹到布萊德比特
we didn't get a chance to see dallala
我們沒有機會看到達拉拉
But we have seen many interesting geological phenomena in the plateau mountains
但是我們在高原山看到很多有趣的地質現象
Also see a lot
同時也看到很多
A few photos I'm going to show you right now
我現在要給你看的幾張照片
distant hometown
遙遠的故鄉
There are many Tibetan girls
有很多藏族的姑娘
There are also different costumes for people from different regions
還有不同地區的人不同的服裝
But they are all equally curious
但是都是一樣好奇的
There are Tibetan compatriots
有藏族的同胞
then use this opportunity
然後利用這個機會
Thank you to the other two of our three cobblers
謝謝我們那個三個臭皮匠裡面的另外兩位
We have been doing this create project from the very beginning until now
我們從一開始就要做這個create計畫一直到現在
One is my colleague Professor Luo Qinghua from National Taiwan University
一位是台大的我的同事羅清華教授
The other is Professor Li Tongyi from STU
另外是施大的李通義教授
They are on the plateau, they are suffering from this altitude sickness headache
他們在高原上那個頂著這個高原反應頭痛
Still willing to be my support until now
還願意一直做我的那個支撐一直到現在
So take this time to show you
所以利用這個時候讓你們看看
The one from Game of three
Game of three的那個當年的一支
Then if you go to Tibet
那如果你上了西藏
Working hours in Tibet are mainly in summer
西藏工作時間主要在夏天
There is no way to work in winter
冬天是沒有辦法工作
We can only enter the venue when we are in our appointment
我們在度約的時候才可以進場
It's okay if you don't go out
不出去就還不行
Then I can't work again in July and August
然後七八月的時候又不能工作
Because July and August is the rainy season
因為七八月是雨季來的時候
You see, when it rains in Tibet, it is very troublesome
你看西藏碰到下雨的時候是很麻煩
september october is a good time to work
九月十月是好的工作時間
then november
然後十一月就不行
it's going to snow in november
十一月要開始下雪
But even when working in the summer
但是即便是在夏天工作的時候
Still easy to see like this
還是很容易看到這個樣子
look
你看
especially to northern Tibet
特別到藏北
As long as there is a brook coming down, this is the virtue
只要有溪度下來就是這個德行
So high-level hospitals should not have been to Tibet
所以高級醫院應該沒有上過西藏
otherwise
不然的話
August Snow may be able to write a little easier
八月雪可能可以寫得更容易一點
The field is especially beautiful when it snows
下雪的時候野外特別漂亮
like this one is tibetan steel thirteen
像這個是西藏鋼鐵十三
Thirteen is a mountain range mainly composed of granite
十三主要是花崗岩組成的一個山脈
mountains of granite
花崗岩組成的山脈
When it snows, we call it Yiyiyi
下雪的時候我們叫它一絲一體
you can take pictures like this
就可以拍到這樣子的樣子
But it's snowing and I still have to work
但是下雪還是要工作
Because there is not much time in a year to go
因為一年能去的時間不多
The advantage of being a teacher is that
當老師的好處就是說
You don't have to tell the students to go over by yourself
你自己不用去叫學生走過去
Then work hard during the semester
那在學期裡面認真工作
young people are different
年輕人是不一樣的
There are also high priority sheep in the blood particles
血粒裡面也有很優先的綿羊
like this
像這個樣子
High atomic treasure is this guy
高原子寶是這個傢伙
In short there are curious furry cows that touch near us
總之有好奇的毛牛會在我們附近觸摸
Then their Zibao future products
然後他們子寶以後的產品
Often used on the wall
常常被貼在牆上利用
This is the most successful photo I took on the letter
這個是我在信上拍到自認為最成功的照片
Just made a fool of myself
只是用傻瓜自己拍的而已
So it's not a question of camera skills
所以不是照相技術的問題
It's a question of good scenery
而是風景好的問題
So it was used as a poster
所以被拿來當作海報
a big lake in the south of tibet
在西藏南邊的一個很大的湖
Yang Zhuoyongcuo
叫楊卓雍錯
very beautiful lake
非常漂亮的一個湖
So if you have the opportunity to go to Tibet
所以各位如果有機會去西藏
Don't forget to go to Yang Zhuo Yong wrong
不要忘了要去楊卓雍錯
But there will be altitude sickness
但是會有高山反應
so you have to be mentally prepared
所以你要有心理準備
But in fact, my body is fine.
但是其實我這個身材上去也沒問題
so you should be fine
所以你們應該也沒問題
that such a Tibet
那這樣的西藏
In fact, a serious problem was discovered immediately
其實馬上發現很嚴重的問題
very serious problem is
很嚴重的問題是
because this is the substance of the world
因為這是世界的物質
Research work since the 1990s or early 2000s
在90年代或者是2000年初期以來的研究工作
After being hit easily
很容易就被碰撞以後
The problem of the highland dragon
高原龍生的問題
Or its Global Impact problem
或者它的Global Impact的問題
Therefore, the problems that everyone is doing are mainly on the initiative.
所以大家做的問題都主要主動在
After India collided with Asia
印度跟亞洲碰撞以後
Problems with Tibetan plateau or whole size biomass
西藏高原或整個大小生物質的問題
How did the dragon come into being?
是怎麼龍生的
then how does it change
然後它是怎麼變化的
When you do your research you find out
等到做研究的時候你就發現
Each section is beautifully modeled
每一段弄得很漂亮的模型
all on a very loose pile of sand
都做在一個非常鬆散的沙堆上
A very loose pile of sand is
非常鬆散的沙堆就是
Boundary Conditions Before India's Collision With Asia
印度跟亞洲碰撞之前的邊界條件
very very little data
只有非常非常少的資料
Everyone has done a very little information above
大家都做了一個非常少的資料上面
Start developing its very nice model
開始發展它非常漂亮的模型
so we feel
所以我們就覺得
Maybe someone should do a little guesswork
也許應該有人來做一點苦猜事
We chose this material to make
我們就選了這個材質來做
The structure of the plate or extended circle before the collision
碰撞以前的板塊或延圈的結構
this matter
這件事情
That is, all collision models
也就是所有的碰撞模型的
In fact, the boundary conditions
其實的邊界條件
to study this thing
要研究這個東西
This is the red stone
就是這個紅色的石頭
What we just said here is called steel bottom silk mountain
我們這裡剛才說的叫鋼底絲山
Or we call it steel bottom wire rock mass
或者我們叫它鋼底絲岩體
or more broadly
或者是更廣泛的說
I call this thing the Antis Mountain of South Asia
這個東西我叫它做南亞的安蒂絲山
How did Mount Antis of South Asia come about?
南亞的安蒂絲山是怎麼來的呢
you just thought
你剛剛聯想到
Antis Hill I just introduced
我剛才介紹的安蒂絲山
Enrichment-type impact scars
是增基型的碰撞痕帶
Enlarged type of impact marks, right?
增基型的碰撞痕帶對不對
Is the Pacific plate like Dongying or Huchong
是太平洋板塊像東 穎 或虎沖
to the continental plate of South America
到南美的大陸板塊之下
out of the mountain
出來的山
That mountain is actually mainly
那個山其實主要是
As a human being, I will study the volcanic eruption itinerary of human beings
我做人會研究人會火山噴發行程
if you have been to south america
如果你去過南美的話
you know the main mountain
你就知道那個主要的大山
Each one is a big volcano
一個一個都是大火山
same situation in this place
在這個地方有一樣的情況
If you pull that India out
你如果把那個印度拉出去
pull back
往回拉走
after pulling away
拉走以後
There is an ancient ocean that will come out
就有一個古海洋會跑出來
That ocean is the Tethys Ocean I just mentioned.
那個海洋就是我剛講的特提斯洋
Tethys oceanic plate
特提斯洋海洋板塊
So the oceanic plate is heading north
所以海洋板塊是向北
Hidden sprawl went under the continental plate of South Asia
隱蔓到南亞的大陸板塊下面去了
so before the collision
所以在碰撞以前
the one with the one that creeps northwards
有一個向北隱蔓的那個
Then built a rocky Andes on the edge of South Asia
然後在南亞的邊上造了一個石的安迪斯山
Just before India collided
就是印度碰撞以前
Here is a long-lived Saimai
這裡就有一個壽長的塞脈
like what we saw in the andes today
就像今天我們在安迪斯山看到的那個情況
But this South Asian Andes
但是這個南亞安迪斯山
very low level of research
研究的程度非常低
to its time to the process of its formation
對它的這個時間對它的形成的過程
what happened to the rock that caused it
造成的岩石到底發生了什麼事
There is only very, very little information
只有非常非常少的那個資料
So when we went to Tibet in 2000
所以我們2000年開始上西藏的時候
I decided to make some of this bitter dish
就決定來做一點這個苦菜式
It starts from Gangdi Shishan here
就從岡底石山這裡開始
I like to do Side with that quote from my friend
我喜歡用我的朋友的那個話來做Side
This is my good friend and my bad friend
這是我的好朋友也是壞朋友
because he always bothers me
因為他經常麻煩我
That professor at Oxford University is called Mike Sear
牛津大學的那個教授叫Mike Sear
It's the great expert in the Himalayas
是喜馬拉雅山的那個大專家
Working in the Himalayas for 30 years
在喜馬拉雅山工作了30年了
is oxford university
是牛津大學
He just posted it earlier this year
他今年初剛發了
A science book called The Colliding Continents
一本科普的書叫The Colliding Continents
don't come here often
不怎么过来
Go in and encourage you to buy a copy and take a look
进去鼓励你们去买一本来看一看
my name is mentioned in the middle
中间有提到我的名字
but i like racing a word in it
但我喜欢赛车它里面的一句话
i just said
我刚刚说了
In fact, one word is to say
其实一句话就是说
The first world is the fourth dimension
第一个世界就是第四度空间
The fourth dimension is time
第四度空间就是时间
is empty
就是空
its a university study
它是一个大学的学习
and most importantly
然后最重要的是
it understands everything in the world
它在世界中的所有东西都能理解
this is a saying
这个是一个说法
it can no longer be explained
它不能再解释了
So when studying address evolution or address events
所以在研究地址演化或地址事件
very important thing
非常重要的一个东西
the past ten years
那过去的十年来
Luckily there is a new dating method
很幸运的有一个新的定年方法
It's not really new
其实也不是新的
A dating method was developed by the meal
一个定年方法被供饭的发展起来
There is a strange mineral in the time-lapse
延时里面有一种奇怪的矿物
This mineral is abundant
这个矿物量多
but useful
但是很有用
This mineral is called telling the truth
这个矿物叫告实
English called Zircon
英文叫Zircon
It's that one of those sour speeches
它的那个是一砍告的那个细酸演讲
Its chemical formula is VR-SIO4
它的化學式子是VR-SIO4
So is the Zoccom Decidicates
所以是Zoccom Decidicates
That mineral is very tenacious
那這個礦物非常頑強
it's after the bathroom
它一在洗手間以後
it will grab a certain amount
它會抓有一定量的
then use it for a while to hold it will protect it
然後用了一段時間抓住它會保護它
don't let it go
不讓它流失
Then use a very important placement element
然後用一個很重要的放置性元素
Because it will go through Chanticare and finally become NProduct
因為它會經過Chanticare最後變成NProduct
will become Chan
會變成是Chan
So with this placement system it's fine
所以用這個放置性系統可以很好的
Dating tool or make a nice Geo-Cronometer
定年的工具或做一個很好的Geo-Cronometer
Then in addition to the age that the 6000 system can give
然後除了6000系統可以給年齡以外
tell the truth because it's tall
告實因為它很有高
So the other relative I sued is H
所以告的另外一個親戚是H
This element can be used for original measurement
它這個元素可以做原味的測量
will make very accurate measurements
會做很準確的測量
So that gives you the composition of the Ha isotope
所以可以給你一個Ha同位素的那個組成
So this mineral can give you age at the same time
所以這個礦物同時可以給你年紀
At the same time give you another isotope system
同時給你一個另外一個同位素系統
Can be used as a so-called Isotropic Tracer
可以當作所謂的Isotropic Tracer
can tell you what the source that said it was made of
可以告訴你說它的形成的那個來源是什麼樣子
So that over the past 10 years
所以那個在過去10年來
become an important one
變成很重要的一個
a fixed method
一個定學的方法
But why was it rarely used in the past?
但是過去為什麼運用的很少呢
mainly because it's small
主要是它很小
When each Boss grows in this master
每顆Boss在這個師傅裡面長出來的時候
Often grow into such a thin and long look
常常長成這樣瘦瘦長長的樣子
it will be around the waist
它會腰圍大概就是
About 50 microns to 100 microns
50個micron到100個micron左右的樣子
Micron is Uyghurni here
micron是維吾尼嘛這邊
10-6 anti-meter
10個-6次的防米
So the right eye can't actually see
所以右眼其實是看不到
To be seen under a highly magnified microscope
要在高度放大的顯微鏡底下看到
The length is usually one or two hundred micron
長度通常是一兩百個micron的樣子
Therefore, it was difficult to do precise measurement with the previous technology.
所以過去的那個技術很難做精確的做量
But because of laser technology
但是因為雷射這個技術
is applied to this field of geochemistry
被應用到這個地球化學的領域
very successful over the past ten years
在過去十年來非常成功
So put the laser laser system
所以把雷射 laser system
Plus that jeep technology
再加上那個吉普儀的技術
The technology we commonly use now is called laser ICBMS
我們現在常用的叫 laser ICBMS的那個技術
You can do it very precisely in this small notice
就可以很精確的在這個很小的那個告示裡面做
its right shoulder
它的右肩的
get its right shoulder parity
得到它的右肩的同位數
It is possible to calculate the age of its formation
可以算出它的形成的年紀
can measure what's in it
可以量它裡面的
The composition of Ha isodigits
哈同位數的組成
This mineral now becomes
這個礦物就現在變成
very useful thing
非常有用的那個東西
Because our private program
因為我們這個私立計畫裡面
A lot of factual analysis was done
用了大量的告實分析的工作
The borrowed geologist changed a word
那藉人地質學家就改了一個詞
This is actually a word in Deville
這個其實是Deville裡面的詞
Deville is a temporary company
Deville是暫時公司嘛
Temporary company's original advertisement called
暫時公司原來的廣告叫
Diamond is the best friend of women
Diamond is the best friend of women
So the geologists changed it to say
所以地質學家就把它改成說
Zerchrom is the best friend of geologists
Zerchrom is the best friend of geologists
I give a practical example
我舉一個實際的例子
because my former student
因為我以前的學生
Dr. Meifei Zhu
台大海人所教授的朱美菲博士
sit there
坐在那裡
So it's his job to do a little bit with everyone
所以他的工作來跟大家做一點點
a little more introduction
多一點的介紹
Made by Zhu Meifei
朱美菲做的
Inside the Primarch Gambis in the south of Tibet
在西藏的南邊的甘比斯原體裡面
Score some tell the truth
分數一些告實來
This truth sometimes grows a little blunt
這個告實有的時候會長得發浮一點
Some are slimmer
有的長得比較苗條一點
This is 50micron scale
這是50micron scale
So this is about 100micron crown
所以這個大概100micron crown
This is about 6 or 70 micron crowns
這個大概是6、70個micron crown
In such a small truth
這個這麼小的告實裡面
We can use laser ICPMS technology
我們可以用雷射ICPMS的技術
It's in the contact with National Taiwan University
就是台大對聯系裡面
our laboratory
我們的實驗室
This is a Laser System
这是一个Laser System
Behind this is a small ICM-MS
这后面是一个小的ICM-MS
Spectrum of Inductive Couple and Plasma
叫做感应偶和电浆之谱
very long Chinese translation
非常长的中文翻译
put it together
把它合在一起
Small notices can be made with Laser
可以用Laser打来微小的告示
Laser Beam probably can
Laser Beam大概可以
Make a Micron
使个Micron的
Fraction typed out
Fration打出来的
And send Kalor Gas to Zhipu
以及Kalor Gas送到植谱里面
To analyze its right-shifted system Wei Subizi
去分析它的右迁的统卫素比子
To analyze its Hartung-Western Bizi
去分析它的哈统卫素比子
So like this ZQC Grant
所以像这个ZQC Grant
can play three holes
可以打三个洞
High time for three shots
打三枪用高时
different ages available
可以得到不同的年龄
and the different Ha Tung Wei Suzi
和不同的哈统卫素子
this shot twice
这个打了两枪
Its Core took a shot
它的Core打了一枪
It's Room a shot
它的Room打了一枪
get different ages
得到不同的年龄
Obtaining a different metric ratio
得到不同的统卫素比子
Finally, the result of our analysis is
最后我们分析的结果是
XQC is from India
ZQC is from India
The Room it grows from is local in Asia
它长出来的Room是在亚洲本地
It grows in the south of Tibet
在西藏南邊的時候長出來
So the implication is this telling
所以implication是這個告訴
It was inside a stone
原來是在一個石頭裡面
it is from the indian plate
它是從印度板塊的
Because India is warm and Asian wind is in Hong Kong
因為印度溫亞洲風中港
sent to the crust of the Asian continent
又送到亞洲大陸地殼裡面去
Then in this tell the side length
然後在這個告訴的邊長
one more ring
再多長一個環
It is the ring belt grown from the nutrients in Asia
是亞洲的養分長出來的那個環帶
So there is the Indian Core
所以有印度的Core
Then add Rhoome from the Asian continent
然後再加上亞洲大陸的Rhoome
grow like today
長出今天這樣的
So the title of this final part is
所以最後這部分的題目就是
India's Hidden Input to Tibetan
India's Hidden Input to Tibetan
Originary Review by
Originary Review by
Haffnima Stubbler
Haffnima Stubbler
Transit in my life in circumstance
Transit in my life in circumstance
or Strax that middle detail
或Strax那個中間的細節
I won't talk about it in particular
我就不特別去講它了
Such an application is actually
這樣子的應用其實就是
We can use such a small particle to tell
我們可以用那麼小顆的告訴
It's actually a micro scale thing
其實是micro scale的東西
then after such a small
然後經過那麼小的
Analysis of the original flavor of the cross-thing
那個跨物的那個原味分析
we can discuss
我們可以去討論
Juguan Megascale
俱觀的Megascale的
or the whole plot
或者整個劇情
Danish or Highland Evolution
丹麥或者高原演化
the one like this
這樣子的那個
Ban Guo Zao's question
Ban Guo Zao的問題
Therefore, the ancients said that the tool of health
所以古人說的健維之具
We think there is actually a certain truth in it.
我們覺得其實有一定的道理在裡面
We use such a technique
我們利用這樣的那個技術
Did it on Tibet for the past few years
在過去的幾年在西藏上做的
quite a bit of that work
相當多的那個工作
An example of this is
其中的例子就是
eyeballs like this one or yellow eyeballs
像這個這個眼體或黃色的眼體
or brown eyes
或棕色的眼體
It's what I just said
都是我剛才講的那個
the one from south asia
那個南亞的那個
Dark Thirteen Above
暗地十三上面
the stone out of the ground
出露在地表上的那個石頭
So we go along this south side of Tibet
所以我們沿著這個西藏南邊
do the detailed one
做詳細的那個
no way to detail
沒辦法詳細的
Do more detailed field work
做比較詳細的野外工作
then sample
然後採樣
Then tell the truth
然後做告實定年
followed by petrology
然後伴隨著岩石學
work with geochemistry
跟地理化學的工作
from the south
從南邊
The reference listed here
這裡列的reference
It's me who supervises some graduate students at National Taiwan University
是我在台大指導一些研究生
Coupled with the cooperation with the Beijing Academy of Chinese Sciences
再加上跟北京中文科學院合作
or co-advised graduate students
或者合作指導的研究生
a series of work done
做出來的一系列工作
Actually there are more
其實還有更多
Tracking from the south of Tibet to the southeast
從西藏南邊往東南追蹤
Then the one in South Asia
然後這個南亞的那個
Dark Thirteen can actually be tracked further south
暗地十三其實更往南可以追蹤到
West of Mingnan
明南的西邊
then into Burma
然后进入到缅甸
So I'm now a postdoctoral researcher
所以我现在一个博士后研究员
PhD researcher who works with me
跟我工作的博士研究员
You know he is now
您都显然他现在就是
This is the way to track southeast
就是这边往东南追踪
Work in Myanmar
进到缅甸里面的工作
After arriving in Myanmar
到缅甸以后
You'll be able to do advanced traffic
你就可以做先进的交通
go on some field trips
去做一些野外考察
then take the time
然后把时候
Come back to work in the lab
再回实验室里面来做工作
A South Asian Andy Thirteen
一个南亚的安地十三
or we say
或者我们说
Mianyan is more than 3000 kilometers along the river and lake
棉岩超过3000公里的沿江湖
Cotton rock cheap rose to
棉岩廉升到
South China Sea
南海
On top of Sumatra in Indonesia
进到印尼的苏门达拉上面
Can
可以
we have now
我们现在已经
work has spread to
工作已经蔓延到
Sumatra went up
苏门达拉上面去了
Then it looks like the lake of Andy Thirteen
那这样子安地十三的湖
From South Asia actually across the Pamirs
从南亚其实跨过帕米尔高原
further west into iran
再往西边就进到伊朗
or the range where the elevated
或高架所在的那个范围
I'll take a moment to introduce you
等一下我会花点时间来跟大家做介绍
Students can make a face-to-face discussion
同学们可以做一个拨面来讨论
How did the address of Tibet evolve?
西藏的地址是怎么演化的
Like this article, a north-south instant noodle is drawn
像这个文章里面就画了一个南北向的泡面
The north-south instant noodles are probably this place
南北向的泡面大概是这个地方
Draw a north-south instant noodle
画一个南北向的泡面
Say from India to the interior of Tibet
说从印度到西藏的内部
or how the interior of Asia might change
或到亚洲的内部可能是怎么变化的
from 65 million years ago
从6500万年以前
There is the time when the new generation begins
有就是新生代开始的那个时间
Then it gradually changed to what it is today
然后渐渐变到今天的样子
Tibet draws a north-south instant noodle
西藏画一个南北向的泡面
It's the south, it's the north
就是南边就是北边
So this side is India and this side is Asia
所以这边是印度 这边是亚洲
we guess or we speculate
我们猜 或者我们推测
Or we propose a model that says
或者我们提出一个模型说
it should look like this
它应该是这个样子
First two plates collide
先两个板块碰撞
Then there is a green plate in front called
然后前面有一个绿色的板块叫做
Ocean Plate of Tethyslan
特提斯兰的海洋板块
One action is that it has to be detached first
一个动作是它要先被detached掉
stripped off
被剥离掉
Because after the two road-grabbing plates collided,
因为两个抓路板块碰撞以后
This heavier oceanic plate
这个比较重的海洋板块
will fall off
一会脱落
Like a drag gong called a Slap Breakup
像拖鑼叫做Slap Breakup
The road and Asia began to collide violently
路跟亞洲開始做劇烈的碰撞
after a violent collision
劇烈的碰撞以後
Asia's plate is relatively soft
亞洲的板塊比較軟
The Indian plate is colder and harder
印度板塊比較冷也比較硬
So it will cause the Asian board to drill the board
所以會造成亞洲板鑽板
Then it became like this
之後就變成這個樣子的
stubborn
嘴硬
Because of the balance of gravity
因為重力均衡的關係
Then something sinks under the Asian plate
然後亞洲板塊底下會有一東西沉下去
drag the gong and sink
拖鑼然後沉下去
This action we call
這個動作我們叫做
Root Foundering
Root Foundering
The Chinese translation seems to be called to follow
中文翻譯好像叫去跟
or split function
或者叫拆成作用
So we think that during the formation of Tibet
所以我們認為在西藏形成的過程中
Breakup with a special thought section
有一個特地思想板塊的Breakup
Then there is a thickened asian plate
然後有一個增厚的亞洲板
The role of the dismantling of the Asian plate
亞洲板塊的拆除的作用
In the end it became what it is today
最後變成今天這個樣子
Of course, there is no way to talk about the process of the department in detail.
當然沒辦法仔細去說講系的過程
That
那
When the actual Breakup happened
實在Breakup發生的時間
Probably in the address history
大概是在地址歷史裡面的
fifty million years ago
五千萬年以前
Fifty MA occurred at that time
五十個MA那個時候發生
because how do we know
因為我們怎麼知道呢
Because we found a lot of records of magma activity on it
因為我們在上面找到很多岩漿活動的記錄
So using these records of magmatic activity
所以利用這些岩漿活動的記錄
And come out sticky controls are all this time
並出來黏黏的控制都是這個時間
So draw a picture of instant noodles at that time
所以那個時候畫一個泡面圖
The detailed diagram is probably at this level
詳細連圖大概是這個等級
At that time, the upper and lower plates or the earth's crust are sucked
那個時候吸上底下的板塊或者地殼
or the lithosphere is not thick
或者岩石圈厚度並不厚
relatively thin
相對是一個比較薄的
So there's an asthenosphere of convection coming up
所以有一個湧上來的對流的軟流圈
That sounds too professional
這樣好像講得太專業了
But the so-called time when
但是所謂這個時間產生的時候
It causes the geochemistry of magmatism
它造成岩漿作用的地球化學性質
will also change with
也會隨著變化
For example, the 50 million years just mentioned
例子是剛才講的是五千萬年
Fifty million years of this virtue
五十個百萬年的時候是這個德性
But we can draw a noodle diagram
但是我們可以畫一個泡面圖
because we're using the time stamp as a guide
因為我們在用時間痕作標的指導
That's sixty million years
就是六十個百萬年
fifty million years
五十個百萬年
forty million years
四十個百萬年
thirty million years
三十個百萬年
we are south of west
我們在西方的南邊
Specimens dating back 60 million years can be collected
可以採到六千萬年前的標本
50 million year old specimen
五千萬年前的標本
40 million year old specimen
四千萬年前的標本
That picture is right
那畫對
There is a detailed earth year for the geochemical analysis to see
有一個詳細的地年在讓地球化學的那個分析看到
Since 50 million years
從5000萬年開始呢
The nature of the created igneous rocks or magmatic activities is different.
造出來的火塵岩或岩漿活動的那個性質就不一樣了
It has different Lensinum etubium
它有不同的Lensinum etubium
The Racial change
的那個Racial的變化
There are different C variations for these two elements
有不同的C對於這兩個元素的變化
This has a change that tells us that
這個有一個變化告訴我們說
The chemistry of the magma that formed was different
形成的岩漿的化學性質不一樣了
My earlier narration said
我前面的講述說
Magma chemistry reflects differences in plate tectonic environments
岩漿的化學性質會反映板塊構造環境的不一樣
right
對不對
The Bagel knowledge of some research and geochemistry told us that
那有的研究學跟地球化學的那個Bagel knowledge告訴我們說
The chemistry that produces this ingredient in this way
這樣子產生這種成分的那個化學
The chemical nature of the magma is a signal that the crust is beginning to thicken
化學性質的那個岩漿是地殼開始增厚以後的訊號
That is, since 50 million years ago
也就是說從5000萬年以來
The crust in the south of Tibet began to gradually thicken
西藏南邊的那個地殼開始漸漸的增厚
So the pen quality of the element in the magma it creates
所以它造出來的岩漿它的那個元素的那個筆質
or its protogeochemical signature
或者它原地球化學的特徵
will follow the magma from 50 million years ago
會跟5000萬年以前的岩漿
are different
是不一樣的
May I
可以嗎
So if we go back to this cartoon
所以如果再回到這個卡通的話
just tell us
就告訴我們說
India and Asia collide
印度跟亞洲開始碰撞
hit hard
碰撞得很厲害
this is cold and hard
這個是又冷又硬的
also hardness plate
也硬度板塊
This is relatively warm and soft
這個是相對暖而比較軟化的
The Asian plate begins to thicken
亞洲板塊就開始增厚
So this one looks thin
所以這個看起來薄薄的一個
This Asian plate is gradually thickening
這個亞洲板塊就漸漸增厚
thickened to what it is today
增厚到今天的樣子
today's appearance
今天的樣子
Why are we talking about crust thickening?
為什麼要特別講地殼增厚呢
because under Tibet
因為在西藏底下
There is currently the last continental crust on Earth
有目前地球上最後的大陸地殼
if you remember
如果你還記得
My classmates in high school may all remember it clearly
高中的同學可能都記得很清楚
earth science textbook
地球科學課本裡面
I told us that the average thickness of the continental crust is
我告訴我們說大陸地殼平均的厚度是
40 kilometers, right?
40公里嘛對不對
The thickness of the crust below Tibet is
跟在西藏底下的地殼厚度是
Average to twice the thickness of the Earth's crust
平均到地殼厚度的兩倍
after it reaches 80 kilometers
它達到80公里以後
So all geological issues in Tibet
所以所有研究西藏的地質問題
or anyone who constructs evolutionary problems must explain
或構造演化問題的人都必須要解釋
why it can thicken up to 80 km
為什麼它可以增厚到80公里
What we know from the geochemical evidence
我們從地球化學的那個證據告訴我們
50 eight years later
50個八年以後
On cue that he started Dico started thickening
在暗示說他開始 第科開始增厚
So this thickening time is
所以這個增厚的時間是
After a lot, you can go all the way to today's 70 to 80 kilometers
後很多 可以一直後到今天的70到80公里
There will be a special research area when the first section is thickened
第科增厚的時候會有一個特殊研疆
This particular research has a special jargon
這個特殊研疆有一個特別的那個 jargon
called aedakites
叫做 aedakites
Chinese called aedakite
中文叫 aedakite
When we were in 2003
我們在2003年的時候
First found in the south of Tibet
第一次在西藏的南邊發現
The special research boundary melted by this thickened crust
這種增厚的地殼所融融出來的特殊研疆
made a report
做了一個報導
aedakite that thing
aedakite的那個東西
such a report
這樣的那個報導
Later in that geotubes it was quoted that
後來那個 geotubes 裡面引用說
This is a very important new discovery in research and inspection
這是研視學裡面當年很重要的一個新的發現
new discovery
新的發現
So I got this from that wikipedia
所以我這個是從那個 wikipedia 上面
the thing that leaked
那個當漏下來的東西
Emphasis on aedakite
特別強調說 aedakite
Inside that photo bag where continents collided
在大陸大陸碰撞的那個照片袋裡面
Thin barriers can appear
像細障可以出現
The cited reference is 4
引的reference是4
This is our article
就是我們這個文章
when i was in class
我在上課的時候
often take this thing out
常常把這個東西拿出來看
Take it out and show it to the students
拿出來給同學看
Then do a little more introduction
然後做多一點的介紹
It was a study class at that time
那時候是研習學的課
can be more detailed
可以講得比較詳細
But if you are naughty, just say
但是有玩皮的學就說
Can Wikipedia be edited by yourself?
Wikipedia是自己可以上去改的嘛
So he said the teacher is filled in by yourself
所以他說老師是你自己填上去的
I really didn't fill it in
真的不是我填上去的
You are welcome to go up and have a look
你們歡迎去上面去看看
If you remember Adkite
如果你記得Adkite的話
but
但是
Please don't delete this one on purpose
請不要把故意把這一條刪掉
The journal is called Geology
這個期刊叫Geology
I just said that the American Area Society
剛才說美國地區學會的
Special journals have made special statistics
專門的期刊特別統計了一下
past eleven or eleven years
過去十一年或十一年來的
The so-called highly sighted paper
所謂highly sighted paper
We have exactly two articles including that one
我們正好有兩篇包括那一篇
The other one was made by teacher Zhu Meiwei just now
另外一篇是剛才朱美威老師做的
What's in a doctoral dissertation
博士論文裡面的東西
two in
兩篇排在
Inside of the top three reference names for each year
每一年的前三名的引用名的裡面
So in this big pie chart
所以在這個大餅圖裡面
Taiwan is squeezed into this small, very small gorge
台灣就擠到這個小小很小的那個峽鳳
this is bragging
這個是吹牛的東西
so try not to talk
所以盡量不講
In addition to studying the South Asian Andy Thirteen
除了研究那個南亞的安地十三以外
Since you have done so much telling the truth
既然做了那麼多告實的那個工作
telltale work can
告實的工作可以
In fact, it is helping us to do another
其實在幫我們在做另外一個
Things related to the research and development of South Asian terrane structure
南亞地體構造研發有關的東西
It's the one here who rises from the mountain
就是這裡的那個照山龍起
With the climate of this Southeast Asia
跟這個東南亞的氣候
and even the development of the river system
乃至於河流水系的那個發育
have a very close relationship
有非常密切的關係
It is the development map of today's water system
就是今天的水系的那個發育圖
But in the past in the history of Earth Day
但是在地球日史的過去
In this case, before the Indian collision
在這裡來說就是印度碰撞來之前
Isn't there an ancient ocean ahead?
前面不是有一個古海洋嗎
That ancient ocean is called special breeding
那個古海洋叫特地飼養
So before India collided
所以在印度碰撞之前呢
I believe there are many rivers here
這裡的河流相信有很多河
Actually it's not east
其實並不是東流的
Instead, it flows westward into this ancient Mediterranean
而是往西流到這個古地中海
Or specially kept inside
或者是特地飼養裡面去
It is because of this collision that the ocean
就是因為這個碰撞把這個洋
This ancient ocean is closed
這個古海洋關閉了
Then the terrain rises
然後這個地形龍起
So all new rivers go east
所以所有新的河流都往東
or flow southeast
或者往東南來流
So there is a topic to study that
所以就有一個課題去研究說
The collision process from no collision to the beginning of the collision to the current situation
碰撞過程從沒有碰撞到開始碰撞到碰撞到今天這個情況
How did the major water systems and major rivers in Southeast Asia develop?
東南亞的主要的水系主要的河流是怎麼發育的
This can be done as a so-called South to think
這個可以做一個所謂的South to think
The environment from the original to the grade is called South
從原到成績的那個環境叫South
Related research from the original meeting
原到會的相關的研究
Because of the dissolution of the plateau, it is in the off sea of ​​Southeast Asia
因為高原的溶解所以在東南亞的外海上
Now there are so many young Chen Jiwu
現在有非常非常多的年輕的陳基物
The young Chen Jiwu has a lot of facts to do related research work
年輕的陳基物裡面有很多告實可以做相關的研究工作
The truth in this Chen Jiwu or the truth from the time of marriage
這個陳基物裡面的告實或親時下來的告實
There is a proper term called Detrital Zochron
有一個專有名詞叫做Detrital Zochron
Chinese is called the truth of debris
中文叫做碎屑的告實
It's the confessions from the time of the relatives
就是親時下來的那些告實
So we can go and study the age of the detritus' truth
所以我們可以去研究碎屑的告實裡面年齡
Analyze its age, analyze its Hartung number
分析它的年齡分析它的哈統為數
and trace its source
然後追蹤它的來源
Let's discuss the process of the river's pro-time transportation and accumulation
來討論河流親時搬運堆積的那個歷程
Right on the plateau we can study the stones on the plateau
就在高原上我們可以研究高原上的石頭
So struck
So struck
after that
然後再
The main river will be developed under the plateau
高原底下會研製這個主要的河流
grab the sand inside
去抓裡面的沙子
Go study the debris notice inside
去研究裡面的碎屑告示
Then the mountain can be compared with the mountain
然後山上跟山下可以做對比
Can see a lot of things that others can't see
可以看到很多別人看不到的東西
or something that no one has seen before
或以前的人沒有看到的東西
In the materials I gave you again, an oiler said
我再給你們那些資料裡面寫了一個打油師說
A few grains of notice to make mountains
幾粒告示搞造山
It's about this story
就是跟這個故事有關
At that time, this one had very long hair
那個時候是這一位頭髮非常長
very elegant graduate student
非常飄逸的研究生
Wearing a very red and very bright coat on Tibet
穿著非常紅非常鮮豔的外套在西藏上
This is Yalu Tibetan wood pulp
這是牙魯藏木漿
Then ask his seniors and sisters to help him collect specimens
然後讓他的學長會學姐一起幫他採標本
I picked some sand and came back
就採了一些沙子回來
Then analyze the debris notice inside
然後分析裡面的碎屑告示
Then find a way to use
然後想辦法利用
For that boundless imagination
那無邊際的那個想像力來說
What kind of connections are there in the middle?
這個中間到底有一些什麼樣的連結
There's a lot of fun in there
這中間有很多好玩的東西
But I can't tell you carefully
但是我沒有辦法仔細跟你說
in order to track down this thing
為了要追蹤這個東西
So we ran down the hill
所以我們跑到山腳下去了
good
好
India can't go to India
印度 印度去不了
So only with Indians India
所以只有跟印度人印度
while collaborating on this
同時合作到這個
The lower reaches of the Yarlung Zangmu River are called
這個亞魯藏牧江的下游叫做
brahmaputra r.
布拉馬普特拉河
if you remember to do
如果你記著做的話
I couldn't remember it at first
一開始記不準面的
English is called Bama Putra
英文叫Bama Putra
Bama Putra is this
Bama Putra是這個
one of the most important rivers in this place
這個地方最重要的河流之一
Then go east and enter the Irrawaddy River
然後再往東就進入到伊羅瓦底江
Then go east and enter into
然後再往東就進入到
A series of Southeast Asian personnel that river
一系列的東南亞人員那個河流
This is what our work looks like in the Irrawaddy
這是我們在伊羅瓦底江工作的樣子
none of the jobs
都沒有工作
It was this girl who knocked the stone hard
是由這個女生努力的敲石頭
Then in the Irrawaddy River to pick
然後在伊羅瓦底江裡面去採
sand
沙子或採它名稱碎穴告石
Finally we now build
最後我們現在建立了
good that data base
很好的那個data base
Along this South Asia's Mount Iss
沿著這個南亞的伊斯山
we picked a lot of that
我們採了很多那個
the hard rock from the middle
那個硬石頭從中間
analyze the age of its telltale stone
分析它的告石的年紀
with the host
跟同位宿主持人
The one that also analyzes rocks
同時也分析岩石的那個
Geochemistry Moderator
地球化學主持人
then follow this river
然後再沿著這個河流
major river system
主要的河流水系
Then next to the water system of the water system
然後在水系的水系的旁邊
The sand or the bottom that deposits locally inside
沙或底下的那個沉積本地裡面
Mined a lot of cave stones
採了很多碎穴告石
I hope that the research on the mountain and the mountain can be coordinated
希望山上跟山下的研究可以配合起來
Look up and down or research this from Softs to Think
上下求其所或從Softs to Think來研究這個
Zhaoshantai is deep and the one received by Boshi at the bottom of the mountain
照山台深然後波石在山底下接到的那個
that thing that was recorded
那個曾經記錄的那個東西
This is my first grad student to tell the truth
這是我第一個說實話的研究生
Xiao Tang's work team of graduate students who just graduated this summer
小唐今年暑假剛畢業的研究生的工作隊
Myanmar made some fun stuff
緬甸做了一些好玩的東西
but i can't go on
但是我不能再說下去
Because I'm going to go into Topic 2
因為我要進入進到主題二
Otherwise I take up too much time
要不然我就佔太多時間了
The second theme is after we have done some work here
主題二就是我們在這邊做了一部分工作以後
I think we should go west to do some comparative work
就覺得說我們應該再往西邊去做一些對比的工作
The most important reason why contrast works is that
對比的工作最重要的原因是
As I said earlier this is a mature crash photo seatbelt
我前面說的這是一個成熟的碰撞照安帶
It started to collide about 60 million years ago
它開始碰撞時間大概是六千萬年左右
Mature banging takes big tits
成熟的碰撞照安帶那麼大的山脈
there is a lot to study
有很多值得研究的東西
But it has a very important disadvantage
但是它有一個很重要的缺點
The downside is the record early in the collision
缺點就是碰撞早期的紀錄
Overshadowed by later or later records
被晚期或後期的紀錄給引蓋了
or was destroyed
或者被摧毀掉了
so many steps
所以很多步驟
Because I can't find it here or I can't see it completely
因為在這裡找不到或看得比較不完全
We just want to find the west sky
我們就想找到西天區
This is a younger, more initial collision state
這是比較年輕的、比較初始狀態的碰撞狀態
In that place we can find records of the early days of the continental continental collision
在那個地方我們可以找到大陸大陸碰撞初期的紀錄
Finally, I hope to combine the states of these two different periods together.
最後希望把這兩個不同時期的狀態合在一起
we'll have a chance to see the collision state start
我們就有機會看到碰撞狀態開始
and then until the evolution to the mature stage
然後一直到演化到成熟階段的演化過程
It was a very simple idea when designing this time
這次當初設計的時候很簡單的想法
After doing it for a few years now, I realize that's not the case at all.
現在做了幾年以後發現根本不是那麼回事
But I can't tell you the details
但是我不能告訴你們詳細
I still have to tell you
我還是要告訴你們說
Our logic is designed like this
我們的邏輯是這樣設計的
And then funded by Congress's court program
然後得到國會會的公廷計畫的資助
It's a good thing that teacher Lu Luoquan didn't come today.
還好今天那個呂羅全老師沒來
Otherwise he might condemn me
要不然他可能會譴責我
What I want to do is these two mountains or these two large plateaus
想做的東西就是這兩個山或這兩個大高原
can we do one thing
我們能不能做一件事
It is to use a story to describe the evolution of these two industries
就是用一個故事來說這兩個工業的演化
The Tibetan Plateau next to this system
這個系統旁邊的西藏高原
The country over there is called the CIA Plateau
那邊的國家叫做CIA高原
It's Gao Jiasuo plus Iran plus Anatolia
是高家所加上伊朗加上安納托利亞
He is called CIA by name
顧名叫他做CIA
Koken
高研
People can write Shuang Cheng Ji
人家可以寫雙成記
A Tale of Two Cities
A Tale of Two Cities
we might be able to
我們也許可以
I have a pattern called A Tale of Two Pathos
我一個模式叫A Tale of Two Pathos
to this place
到這個地方來說
can think of something right now
馬上可以想到一些
something to do with history
跟歷史有關的東西
in fact
跟特提式洋其實
Many concepts related to Greek mythology
很多的觀念跟希臘神話
There are many stories in it
裡面的故事有很多
words like here
像這裡的話
Immediately thought of Persia
馬上想到是波斯
Because from Iran to Anatolia
因為從伊朗到安納托利亞
They are actually of the Persian race.
其實都是波斯的那個種族
Then this picture is for you to see
然後這個圖是給你看叫
Map of Alexander the Great
亞利山大大地的版圖
if you remember
如果你還記得
the words of that hollywood movie a few years ago
幾年前的那個好萊塢電影的話
so here we go
所以我們到了前進
to iran
到伊朗
Immediately see a lot of Persian architecture
馬上就看到很多波斯的建築
Tehran is the capital of Iran
伊朗的首都叫德黑蘭
Tehran is a very ugly city
德黑蘭是一個非常醜的城市
Then it is very discouraged to go
然後非常不鼓勵大家去
but tehran has one
但是德黑蘭有一個
iran has one
伊朗有一個
The current second largest city is Isfahan
目前的第二大城叫伊斯法寒
in the south
在南邊
Isfahan is a very important
伊斯法寒是一個很重要的
The ancient city of Persia
那個波斯的古城
Then the Iranians themselves said
然後伊朗人他們自己都說
istan represents half of the world
伊斯坦代表世界的一半
Half of the world
Half of the world
There are many places worth visiting in the middle
中間有很多值得去的地方
Then this is taken from the webpage in Ma Youyou's private plan
那這個是從馬悠悠的私度計畫裡面的網頁摘來的
So if you want to broadcast something about Persia
所以如果想播看一點波斯的有關的東西
other than music
除了音樂以外
In fact, on the webpage of Ma Youyou's private plan
其實在馬悠悠的私度計畫的網頁上
There are many beautiful photos
有很多很漂亮的照片
Professional-grade photos we can't get
我們拍不到的專業級的照片
when you go to iran
那你在伊朗去的時候
Immediately encountered a lot of different things
馬上碰到很多不一樣的東西
This photo is on the poster
海報上有這個照片
You'll see reports on CNN or BDC
你會看到跟CNN或BDC報導
something very different
非常不一樣的東西
There are very, very friendly fellow villagers
有非常非常友善的老鄉
very kind people
非常善良的老百姓
have very blue sky
有非常藍的天空
There is very sour oil that is not very tasty
有非常酸不怎麼好吃的石油
and then there's korankin, which is everywhere
然後有到處都有的可蘭金
And then you'll often run into some desert climate stuff
然後你會常常會碰到一些沙漠氣候的東西
so there is a hot sun
所以有很熱的太陽
But these when you have good geological phenomena can be seen
但是這些當你有很好的地質現象可以看
it doesn't matter
都沒關係
I have many photos of Iran
我有很多伊朗照片
But I can't show you one by one
但是不能給你一一的看
If you push further west in Iran
如果在伊朗再往西邊推的話
Arrived at the viaduct
就到了高架所
This is the scenery of Daejiao Suo Mountain in spring
這是大高架所山春天的風景
very different from iran
跟伊朗非常不一樣
above iran you see
在伊朗上面你看到
mostly desert climate stuff
大部分是沙漠氣候的東西
then you get to the elevated
然後你到了高架所
you see a lot of green things
你就看到很多綠色的東西
The elevated mountain has something to do with Greek mythology
那高架所山又跟希臘神話有關係
Because there is a prome
因為有一個叫做普羅米
Hughes fell here
修斯的人掉在這裡
Prometheus is the movie from last year to the year before
普羅米修斯就是去年還前年的那個電影
I'm very interested
我看得很有興趣
Because of the relationship with the elevated
因為跟高架所有關係
The giant who was punished by Kanari
被奏持處罰的那個巨人
The giant hand hangs on a cliff at the Great Elevated Station
巨手就掛在大高架所的一個懸崖上
The liver that accepts Lao Yin to eat him day after day
日復一日的接受老印來吃它的那個肝
leaver
leaver
Is such that
是這樣的
So when I went to the elevated station
所以我到高架所去的時候
just try hard to find the cliff
就很努力去找懸崖
Check for Prometheus
看看有沒有普羅米修斯
see a lot of beautiful scenery
看到很多好看的風景
But without Prometheus
但是沒有普羅米修斯
But there are many beauties in elevated places
但是有不少高架所的美女
But not always so lucky
但是不是每次運氣都那麼好
Like this aluminum one seems to like my look better
像這隻鋁一隻看來就比較喜歡我的樣子
Then push to the west and go quickly.
那這往西邊再推很快的過去
because my business should be coming soon
因為我的事情應該快到了
to Türkiye
到土耳其
Türkiye has so many things to mention
土耳其有非常非常多值得提的東西
except address
除了地址以外
But I can only give you three examples
但是只能舉三個例子給你們看
show you this
這個給你看
Servo project by Red Pit
Red Pit做的伺服計畫
he ran to that from the west
他從西方跑到那個
Inside the Troy Coming Movie
木馬圖城記的特洛伊來的電影裡面
The god of war who played the legend
演那個傳奇的那個戰神
Akievez's movie
阿基維茲的那個電影
watched several times
看了好幾遍
but what about the story
但是故事是怎麼樣
If you are interested in
如果你有興趣
I'll talk to you later when we're free
等一下我們有空的話再跟你聊
Then this place is actually
那這個地方其實跟
Alishan's Great has a great relationship
阿里山的Great有很大的關係
Your memorial to Turkey from the west
你到土耳其的紀念從西邊
next to the sea of ​​love or greece
就在愛情海或希臘的旁邊
Especially the South China Sea along this sea of ​​insects
特別是沿著這個地蟲海的南海
i have been to iran
我一直到伊朗
you see a lot
你都看到非常多
Alishan, what was left behind when Alishan came to the earth
阿里山 亞里山到大地當初留下來的
Historic sites
歷史遺跡
very very spectacular special
非常非常壯觀 特別
you can see a lot
你可以看到很多
But apart from these two movies
但是除了這兩個電影以外
Another thing that is more important to me is this mountain
還有一個更重要跟我有關的是這個山
this mountain is a volcano
這個山是一個火山
The name of the mountain is Mong Aralats
山的名叫Mong Aralats
Aralats is a holy mountain
Aralats是一個聖山
Two Holy Mountains of Meat in Islam and Christianity
回教跟基督教的兩個肉聖山
This way you will think it is very troublesome
這樣子說你會想到是很麻煩
I also know that probably in Turkey
我也知道大概在這個土耳其的
The easternmost country is Armenia
最東邊在亞美尼亞這個國家
Near the border with Turkey
跟土耳其的那個交界附近
is in the bible
是聖經裡面
When the Great Flood Occurs in the Bible
聖經故事裡面大洪水發生的時候
Where the Loya's Ark stands
洛亞方舟挺靠的地方
We are going to study this mountain next year
我們明年要去研究這個山
So if someone signs up
所以如果有人報名
consider
考慮
we this year
我們今年
we are here today
我們今天來了
The place that did the work is here
做了工作的地方在這裡
in the southeast of Türkiye
在土耳其的最東南邊
It's on the border of Syria and Iraq.
就是敘利亞跟伊拉克的邊上
almost never go
差一點就去不了
If the United States goes to fight Syria
如果美國去打敘利亞的話
Good thing he didn't hit
還好他沒有打
so we're here to do a job
所以我們來這邊做個工作
Be a geological phenomenon
做個地質現象以外
Next to this is Iraq, right?
這個旁邊是伊拉克對不對
Iraq is two river basins
伊拉克是兩顆流域
One of the powers of civilized speech
文明發言力之一
This thing can be seen while running out of Türkiye
在土耳其跑出來的時候可以看到這個東西
This is the source or upstream of the six-shot bottom box
這個是六發拉底盒的源頭或上游的地方
So you can do address stepping on my drug specimen here
所以你可以做地址踩我藥的標本在這裡
At the same time, you can take pictures like this
同時可以拍到這種的相片
So every time Mr. Peng said that I went to visit mountains and rivers everywhere
所以每次的彭老師都說我到處去游山聞水
still get money from congress
還可以拿國會的錢
So that's the picture of Curtis in it
所以就是這個科提斯照片在裡面
A very important research address
非常重要的一個研究地址
We call it Type Locality
我們叫它做Type Locality
Because Türkiye has a special collision modeling effect
因為土耳其有特殊的碰撞造型作用
The Turks call it the Origin of Turkish Type
土耳其人叫它做Turkish Type的Origin
Turkic modeling movement
叫土耳其式的造型運動
because it's like cartoon books 84 million years ago
因為它就像卡通圖書在84個百萬年前
between arabia and asia
阿拉伯跟亞洲碰撞之間
It's not just two big plates colliding
它不是兩個大板塊碰撞而已
A lot of small microplates are added in the middle
中間還加了很多小小的microplates
How did these microplates evolve?
這些microplates到底是怎麼演化
How did the action come about?
到底是怎麼形成的動作
How to do the interaction in the middle
中間是怎麼樣做interaction的
Actually a lot of people have interesting address questions here
其實有很多人有趣的地址問題在這裡
So I say it is actually a sandwich-style collision modeling movement
所以我說它其實是三明治式的碰撞造型運動
Except for two pieces of toast
除了兩塊吐司以外
There is a lot of material in the middle
中間有很多材料在中間
waiting for a geologist to do it
等待地質學家去做
to parse it
去解析它
That's what it looks like now
那現在的樣子變成這樣子
It's all crowded together
這個上面之多全部都擠在一起
what to do in the middle
要怎麼樣在中間
This separates his material piece by piece
這個把他的那個材料一塊塊的分開來
Then tell us what's going on with the R&D here
然後告訴我們說這裡研發的情況到底是怎麼樣
how to solve this place
怎麼樣去解決這個地方
The so-called Tectonic Curse Rule in Geology
所謂地質學上的Tectonic Curse Rule
structural substance
構造上的那個實質物口
There are many, many issues worthy of research
有很多很多值得研究的問題
so we went on a raid
所以我們去突擊的
The most important reason to work is to
工作的最重要原因是想
think about researching this
想想去研究這個問題
when setting up this plan
設定這個計畫的時候
quickly
很快的
We design three main studies of that interest
我們設計三個主要研究的那個興趣
will study the work area
會研究工作區域
Study this northernmost point in Arabia
研究這個阿拉伯的最北邊
Crash Peak and lead north
碰撞峰和帶領北邊
we from the southeast of iran
我們從伊朗的東南邊
That is, near the border between Iran and Pakistan.
也就是伊朗跟巴基斯坦的邊界的附近開始
Then follow this to the northwest
然後沿著這個往西北邊追蹤
Then finally go to the Protos of this CEIA
然後最後到這個CEIA的那個Protos上面
There are a lot of green things after the collision
有很多綠色的東西是碰撞以後
research activity
造出來的那個研究活動
we want to do with these things
我們想對這些東西做
Then new observations then suggest that we are in this place
然後新的觀察 然後提出我們在這個地方
have new explanations or models
有新的解釋或模型
I'll show you a few examples soon.
那很快的給大家看幾個例子
This is my job as a PhD student
這是我一個博士生的工作
just along this usual place
就沿著這個常常的這個地方
I call it the Gangdi Stone Mountain in West Asia
我叫它做西亞的岡底石山
Or the Antistone Mountains in West Asia
或者是西亞的安蒂石山
OK so again
OK 所以 again
Let's do this first and pull this arabic block out
我們先做這個把這個阿拉伯本塊拉出去
Then attribute the ancient Mediterranean or this special ocean to the
然後把古地中海或這個特地師洋歸付
Then Tedi Shiyang went north to do hidden work at that time
然後特地師洋那個時候是往北做隱蔛作用
Here to create something like today's Gangdi Stone Mountain
在這裡造出一個像今天的岡底石山一樣的東西
Let's get to know its time distribution
我們去了解它的時代分布
Then its rock-technical tailoring
然後它的岩石技術化的特身
and then to understand what the structure of the place looked like before the collision
然後去了解碰撞以前這個地方的結構是什麼樣子
It takes a little hard work like this
這樣子需要做一點苦工
no one has done it before
以前人都沒有做過的
My doctoral research
我這個博士生研究研究
This Gangdi stone mountain in West Asia has done a series of sampling and analysis work
這個西亞的岡底石山做了一系列的採樣跟分析工作
This Gangdi Stone Mountain has a special name
這個岡底石山有一個特殊的名字
Then there are two place names, the nameless is the lake
然後這是兩個地名,無名也就是這個湖
There is a big lake called Wumingye
這裡有一個很大的湖叫無名也
Dota is that name for a little trip here
Dota是這裡一個小趟的那個名字
Dota, the meaning of Persian painting is simply Dotr
Dota,波斯畫的意思很簡單就是Dotr
So it's easy to remember, the name of that city is Dotr
所以很容易記嘛,那個城的名字叫Dotr
I asked my Iranian friend why the city is called Dotr
我問伊朗朋友說為什麼那個城叫Dotr
He said he didn't know, he couldn't take the test
他說不知道,不可考了
Anyway, this is the belt
Anyway,就是這個belt
We have done the most detailed chronology and geochemistry ever done along this belt
我們沿著這個belt做了有史以來最詳細的年代學跟地球化學的工作
So the paper that published the lead film is the first one
所以那個發表領片paper是第一篇
There will be other things in the future
後續還會有其他的東西
It can be discussed that the initial state of collision orogeny in this place
可以討論說這個地方的碰撞造山的初始狀態
Then what is its boundary condition like?
然後它的邊界條件大概是怎麼樣
More broadly, the so-called Zogras Origin
更廣義的來說,這裡所謂的Zogras Origin
Because the mountain in Iran is called Zogras Mountain
因為伊朗的那個山叫做Zogras Mountain
This location is here, Zogras Mountain is here
這個位置在這裡,Zogras Mountain在這裡
If it corresponds to the east, it is the Himalayas in the south of Tibet.
對應到東邊的話就是西藏南邊的喜馬萊亞山
So the Himalayas in Iran are called Zogras
所以伊朗的喜馬萊亞山叫做Zogras
Then in a broad sense, we call it Zogras Origin
然後廣義的造成運動我們叫它做Zogras Origin
It can also start to control or discuss this thing
它也開始可以去控制或去討論這個東西
The example given is that the end time of the delay event just now is not at the same time
舉的例子是剛才那個延將活動結束的時間是不同時的
This English name is Decronus
這個英文叫Decronus
The translation of the mainland is called time-traversing through time
大陸的翻譯叫做穿時的穿過時間
It's just that the time is different
就是它時間是不一樣的
end time in the northwest
結束的時間在西北邊
Northwest of Iran is about 25 million years
伊朗西北邊是大概25個百萬年
The end of the event will be postponed around 25 million years
2500萬年左右延將活動結束
Then in the middle it becomes 15 million years
然後到中間變成是15個百萬年
end around 15 million years
1500萬年左右結束
It will be about 6 to 7 million years to the south
到南邊大概是6到7個百萬年左右結束
So it ends time gradually towards the south
所以它結束時間往南邊漸漸
The local inspection means that the collision between Arabia and Eurasia in this place is
地檢的意思就是說阿拉伯跟歐亞大陸在這個地方的碰撞是
this place happened first
這個地方先發生了
After the occurrence, the Arab reaction will produce in reality
發生以後阿拉伯反會產生現實中
No Rotation in reverse time
不對 逆時中的旋轉
come up
繞上來
Then turn off this special episode Shiyang in the middle
然後把這個中間的特輯時陽關閉掉
then collide collide together
然後碰撞 碰撞在一起
so this is the place
所以這個是這個地方
The first constraint that prolongs the age of activity
第一個 延將活動年代的那個制約
Let's discuss the role of this collision
來討論說這個碰撞的作用
or that plate suture in this place is
或這個地方的那個板塊縫合作用是
Diaclomus
Diaclomus
Yes, that phenomenon
對 那個那個現象
Then my other postdoctoral fellow is Peng Junneng
那我的另外一個博士後叫彭均能
It's the postdoctoral fellow from Hong Kong
是從香港來的那個博士後
Also did a lot of work locally
也在地方做了很多的工作
and found something very interesting
然後發現了一些很有趣的東西
Because of time constraints, I won't talk about him in particular.
因為時間關係都不特別去講他了
As mentioned earlier, for example,
那前面講的例如說是
we are in some special places
我們在一些特別的地方
Do detailed work on specific issues
針對特別的問題去做詳細的工作
and then to solve
然後去解決
The local or specific geological problem
local的或比較specific的那個地質問題
But in the end I hope to be able to synthesize
但是最後希望可以綜合
Jobs on the west side of the place vs. jobs on the east side
這個地方西邊的工作跟東邊的工作
plus the rest of asia
再加上亞洲其他地方
Included here includes jobs in South East Asia
包括這裡 包括東南亞的工作
From a more macro perspective
可以整個更宏觀的來看
Asian continent
亞洲大陸
The process of evolution of the entire continental crust
整個大陸地殼演化的過程
Because the continent of Asia is the largest in the history of the earth
因為亞洲的那個大陸是地球歷史上
Since the Avatar
從顯身座以來
Xianshen seat is since the beginning of the Five Generations
顯身座就是五生代開始以來
That's about 540 million years ago
也就是五億四千萬年左右以來
The most important is the new continental crust
最重要的有新的大陸地殼
place of growth
生長的地方
Then my teacher Jiang Boming
那我的老師江伯明
A lot of jobs that Asians are doing in the previous one
以前的那個中亞洲人在做的很多的工作
Then we are now in this Tethyste generation
那我們現在在這個特提斯特人代
Or the follow-up work done in the East Tethyste generation
或東特提斯特人代裡面做的後續工作
Finally, you can hope that you can combine
最後可以希望可以combine
something related to this
這個相關的那個東西
Make a more macroscopic explanation of the whole of Asia
做一個整個亞洲更宏觀的解釋
In it it's the finale of my end
那裡面它就是我的結束的那個終曲
But the research is actually halfway through
但是研究其實正在進行到一半
is from 2011
是從2011年開始
To be carried out until 2026
要到進行到2026年
Chinese and English together
中文跟英文加在一起
Pretty nice
蠻好看的
2016 is now exactly in the middle of the third year
2016年現在正好是第三年的那個中間
So it's less than two halves
所以做了兩半不到
Another two and a half years to work
還有另外兩年半要工作
Maybe I can really sing the finale later
也許以後才能真正唱終曲
So before singing the real finale
所以在唱真的終曲以前
Thinking of Bobby
想到Bobby
The famous song is called Blood in the wind
很有名的歌叫做Blood in the wind
there is a line in it
裡面有一句歌詞
i borrow to be my end
我借來做我的結束
說How many years can a mountain exist
說How many years can a mountain exist
before it's washed away to the sea?
before it's washed away to the sea?
The answer is
The answer is
Lowing in the wind
Lowing in the wind
I can't find the answer in minutes
我沒有辦法在分裡面找答案
But we will continue to do our create research project
但是我們會繼續做我們的create研究計畫
hope in the near future
希望在不久的將來
I can introduce more things to you
可以有更多東西跟大家介紹
I'll stop here thank you
我就講到這邊 謝謝
Thanks
謝謝
Thank you Mr. Zhang for this wonderful introduction
謝謝張老師的這個精彩的介紹
And he has good timing
而且他時間控制得很準
It will be over in about 80 minutes
大概就是80分鐘就結束
So we have a lot of time for Q&A
所以我們有蠻多時間的可以Q&A
The first comment is
第一個comment是
I seem to have chosen the wrong line
我好像選錯行
I should learn the address from him
我應該來跟他學地址
that open scenery
那個開風光
OK
OK
ok we open to
好 我們Open to
everyone can ask questions
大家可以提問題
good
好
Then you use your microphone to
那你用你的麥克風對
Press the green one
按那個綠的人就可以
Teacher, can I ask you?
老師能不能請教一下
You just talked about this MD-43 in Asia
您剛剛講到亞洲的這個MD-43
It was originally bent
它是原來就是彎的
Or because it was bent by the Indian continent
或者是因為被印度大陸起成彎的
I thought he was smoother
原來是相信他是比較平滑的
Because India only squeezed after meeting
因為印度碰到以後才擠彎的
When the Frenchman just said
剛剛講的那個法國人講的時候
He escaped, but he didn't
他是逃出去其實不是
If you escape, it's just not a squeeze.
逃出去那是不擠彎而已
No, escaping is another phenomenon
不是 逃出去就是另外一個現象
It actually has something to do with the bending process.
跟擠彎的過程其實有關係
He did come and escape
他的確來逃出去了
But the mechanism by which he escaped
但是他逃出去的機制
will escape time french
會逃出去時間法國人
we think they are wrong
我們覺得他們說錯了
Okay, thank you
好 謝謝
good
好
that teacher
那位老師
Thank you for your introduction
謝謝你剛才說的介紹
Because according to the three generations, the two
因為照三代把這個兩個
Collision of different plate shapes
不同的板塊形態碰撞
Well said
講得不錯
That is, if the oceanic plates collide
就是如果說海洋板塊碰撞的話
I want to generate something like North or South America
我想產生像北美或南美那種
Andis Sanmai
安迪士三脈
This is the so-called rocky rivers and lakes
就是這種有所謂岩江湖的這種
Nazagors or Turkine
那扎古爾斯或者是土耳其寧
Up-to-date on this last PhD study
最新的這個最後面的博士研究
I have a curious
我有一個比較好奇的
I think Taiwan happens to be the same
我想說台灣剛好也是
I have 600 better
我有到600塊更好
Ocean version, but where is the lava lake on our side?
海洋版本,可是我們這邊的岩漿湖在哪裡?
There is a magma lake. The ocean mountain range is mainly a magma lake that travels to the island lake.
岩漿湖有啊,海洋山脈主要就是一個旅送島湖的岩漿湖嘛
Then if you go to the north, Chancellor Mountain, many people say it is a magma lake that continues to Ryukyu Island Lake
然後你到北邊去的話,大臣山,很多人說它是延續到琉球島湖的岩漿湖
so there are still
所以還是有的
It's just that Taiwan's spatial scale is very small
只是台灣的空間尺度很小
So there are certain difficulties in parsing, plus
所以在解析上有一定的困難,再加上
The time scale is very short, and the step of Taiwan is about five or six million years ago
時間尺度很短,台灣的步段大概是五六百萬年以來的事情
Compared with Tibet, Tibet is about 50 to 60 million years old
跟西藏比的話,西藏大概是五六千萬年來的事情
Then its scale is 3,000 kilometers wide. I am more than 3,000 kilometers wide, and Taiwan is only about 300 kilometers long.
然後它的Scale是三千公里寬,我超過三千公里寬,台灣只有三百公里長左右嘛
So time and space belong to Tibet
所以時間空間都是西藏的
One-tenth, one Ode is missing, if one Ode is missing, it can be done in geology
十分之一,差了一個Ode,差了一個Ode的話在地質學上來做起來的話
simulation possible
模擬可能
Space is easy to control, but time is very difficult to control, because the geological time is five or six million years
空間容易控制,但是時間很不好控制,因為地質的時間五六百萬年
In chronology and dating, it is not easy to determine accurately
在年代學,定年學上很不容易定得很準確
So Taiwan has a Taiwan problem
所以台灣有台灣的問題
I also accidentally did some Taiwanese work
我也不小心的做了一些台灣的工作
So if Mr. Peng invites me to come again in the future
所以如果彭老師以後要請我再來的話
Next time I will tell you about Taiwan
下次我就講台灣的給你聽
But Taiwan does have
但台灣的確也有
But there is no way to do a one-on-one parallel
但是跟那裡沒辦法做一對一的平行
Contrast because of the problem of time and space
對比因為有時間跟空間持多的問題
I am a teacher, but
我是老師,但是
I had a question just now and I just forgot to say it
剛才我有一個問題,我剛剛忘記講出來
If it's North America, the one you're talking about
如果是北美的話,跟你們所說的那個
Himalayan side huh? His lava dance is granite
喜馬拉雅這邊的是吧?他的岩漿舞是花崗岩
The problem is we are thinking about Taiwan
問題是我們是在想台灣
Of course I know that the scale is much different, and
我當然知道那個尺度差很多,而且
Because there is an order difference, and both North America and the Himalayas started more than 60 million years ago
因為差了一個 order,而且北美跟喜馬拉雅都是六千多萬年前的開始
Your question is very very good and has been well thought out since I do this
你問題非常非常好,已經考慮得很深入,因為我做這個
Because of time I can't speak too deeply
因為時間我沒辦法講得太深
or too rigid
或者是太刻板了
So simplifies skipping a lot of stuff
所以簡化了跳過很多東西
Many of the three Legis veins in North America are granite rocks
北美的勒吉三脈很多都是花鋼岩
Yes, then Gandisan in Tibet
對 然後西藏的甘迪斯安
It is also mainly granite
也主要都是花鋼岩
We call these flower steel rocks
這些花鋼岩我們都叫它做
Qingluyan in volcanic petrology
青露岩在火山岩石學上
Qingluyan means
青露岩的意思就是說
It wasn't created by a volcanic eruption to the surface
它不是火山噴發到地表產生的
It is after a certain depth underground
它是在地底下一定深度以後
Slowly cools and turns into a green rock mass
慢慢冷卻 然後變成一個青露的岩體
And now it means to come to the surface
然後現在跑到地表上來的意思
like the example of tibetan kandishan
像西藏甘迪斯安的例子
We know Candisian was underground
我們知道甘迪斯安當初在地底下
It's underground, some places are 20 kilometers deep
是在地底下有的地方是20公里深的地方
formed a stone
形成了石頭
Now it's on the surface
現在已經跑到地表上來了
so tell us
所以就告訴我們說
When Tibet was colliding with Taiwan's depth
西藏在碰撞台深的時候
20 kilometers thick on the surface
地表上有20公里厚的
The stone that covered it has been eroded away
蓋著它的石頭被侵蝕掉了
Now it's all moved to the sea
現在都搬到海裡面去了
move into the bay of bengal
搬到孟加拉灣裡面
or other grade powder inside
或其他的成績粉地裡面
for example
譬如說
So it puts the green dew rock under the ground
所以它把地底下的青露岩
Flower dry rock exposure
花乾岩 曝露地
come on the surface
在地表上來
Very different from this is that the Andes are in South America
跟這個很大不一樣是安底斯山在南美
The gate volcanoes of the Andes are all extrusive rocks
安底斯山的大門火山都是噴出岩
called Kanak rocks
叫做Kanak rocks
So it's a volcanic rock
所以它是火山噴出來的石頭
So there should be a lot of dew rocks under it
所以它底下應該有很多清露岩
something like granite
像花崗岩的東西
but not yet exposed to the surface
但是還沒有暴露在地表上來
Then to the example of Iran
那到了伊朗的例子
we actually see the same thing
我們其實看到一樣東西
Inside the Andes Mountains in West Asia, Iran
在伊朗的西亞的安底斯山裡面
We are the young underbelly
我們就那是年輕的遭暗帶
The young samurai compared to the one at the initial stage
年輕的遭暗比較初始階段的那個遭暗
So its body and wave stone are not so powerful
所以它的台身跟波石就沒那麼厲害
So that UDMA there
所以那裡的那個UDMA
The magma fire in West Asia I just mentioned
我剛才說的那個西亞的岩漿火
extrusive rock
上面都是噴出岩
like the andes example
像安底斯山的例子一樣
So the difference between the entire Tibet and the Iranian viaduct is
所以整個西藏跟伊朗高架所的差別是
this is mature
這個是成熟的
So its average altitude is 4500 meters high
所以它的平均海拔是4500公尺高
means it is set high
表示它被台的很高
During the high stage
台的很高的過程中
At the same time there are many things on the surface
同時地表上有很多東西
The cover is smashed
蓋子都被波死了
was moved to sea
被搬到海上
to the west in the iranian caucasus
在西邊在伊朗高加索呢
Its average altitude is only 1000 meters high
它平均海拔只有1000公尺高
The plateau is only 1000 meters high
只有1000公尺高的高原
So it's a younger version of that dirty
所以它是個年輕版的那個細臟
so it's just starting to melt
所以它剛剛開始融身
Peeling isn't that great
剝石還不是很厲害
And the wind in that place is not like the wind in the Indian Ocean
然後那個地方的風不像印度洋有寄風
so not so much moisture
所以沒有那麼多水分
erosion the degree of surface erosion
侵蝕的那個地表侵蝕的程度
much lighter than the east
要比東邊要輕微的多
I have an answer do you have a question
我有回答你有問題嗎
Thank you, teacher
謝謝老師
Our South Australian Edition
我們的南澳版
Does that count?
難道那個算不算
South Australia
南澳
electric eye
電眼
collision collision
碰撞碰撞
So the Great South Australia or
所以那個大南澳或者是
you to telugu country
你到泰魯閣國家
won't you see district nine
你不是會看到九區
Marble, right?
大理岩嗎對不對
I saw a lot of people in the prison area are very powerful
看到很多城牢區的很厲害
Dungeon area
地城牢區
said
表示說
severe deformation
受到的碩性變形
Monolithic not rigid deformation
鐵板一塊不是剛性的變形
Yes or no
是不是
It deformed at a high temperature and pressure
它當初變形的溫度跟壓力都高
If we push the pressure to the depth
如果我們壓力推到深度來說
It should be a stone 10 kilometers underground
它應該是地底下10公里的石頭
it produces that deformation
它產生那種變形
Therefore, in the Taroko National Pressure Industry Co., Ltd.
所以太魯閣國壓工業裡面
Many rocks are about 10 kilometers underground
石頭很多是地底下10公里左右的東西
Then because of the collision with Zhaoshan
然後因為碰撞照山
Then Taishan and then surface wave time
然後台山然後地表波時
now brought to the surface
現在被台到地表上
seen by us
被我們看到
The mechanism is much the same
這個機制是大同小異的
who
那位
Hello teacher, thank you teacher for your wonderful speech
老師好 先謝謝老師精采的演講
what i want to ask is
我想請教的是
as the teacher said at the beginning
就像老師一開始說的
The scale of the teacher's research is very large
老師研究尺度非常的大
But throughout the speech
但是在整個演講中
Always comparing Tibet with the CIA
一直把西藏和CIA那邊相比較
However, what I want to ask the teacher here is to say
然而我在這裡想請教老師是說
Then in such a large-scale comparison
那這樣子大尺度的比較裡面
There are some
有一些
Maybe I don't know it's a violation of influence
也許不知道是違觀影響
or have a major impact
或是說有重大影響
May I ask how do you get rid of this kind of research?
請問您在做這樣的研究怎麼排除掉
For example, just now you mentioned
比方說啦 剛才您有提到
Turkish researchers put their place
土耳其的研究者把他們的那個地方
called a Türkiye shape
稱為是一種土耳其形狀
There are many small plates in the middle
有很多小板塊在中間
then it's like a sandwich
然後是三明治的樣子
Then how can you say
那這時候您怎麼能夠去說
The Turkish one can be used as
土耳其那個可以當作
Early model of Tibet
西藏的早期的模型
Could it be Türkiye because of those little plates in the middle
會不會土耳其因為中間有那些小板塊
So his whole future
所以他的整個將來的
His development is actually different from that of Tibet.
他的發展跟西藏其實是不一樣的
Two stories, so let's say
兩樣故事 所以比方說啦
this place
這個地方
If you're excluding the model of that sandwich
如果你要排除那個三明治的模型的話
would you do this
你會這樣做嗎
that if you want
那如果要的話
Why do you feel like these factors
為什麼你覺得像這些因素
You can choose and exclude, thank you
你可以取舍並且排除 謝謝
Your question is the stuff I'm going to write a thesis on
你的問題就是我要寫一篇論文的材料
so ask him to put you in place
所以問他要給你到位
There's really no way to make a direct comparison.
的確是沒辦法做直接對比
there are many in the middle
中間有很多
I have a slide in front of me
我前面有slide寫
There are many similarities
有很多similarities
many similarities
很多相似的地方
But in fact there are more differences
但是其實有更多的differences
It should be as simple as we think
應該是我們想的很簡單
want its similarities
想要它的 similarities
But after doing this work
但是做了這個工作以後
In fact, finding the differences may be more important
其實發現 differences 可能是更重要的
that needs an explanation
那個需要解釋的地方
or a place worthy of study
或者值得想去研究的地方
So there is really no way to make a professional comparison between the two things.
所以兩個東西的確沒辦法做職業對比
Then there are a lot of details in the middle
然後中間有很多細節的東西
i can't speak
我沒辦法講
Or I'm doing something related right now
或者我現在正在做相關的東西
Eventually is what you point out
Eventually 就是你point out的
there's something we're going to do
有一些東西就是我們正要做的東西
Thanks
謝謝
Hello, professor, what I want to ask is
教授你好我想請教的是
May I ask that the mountain on the light barrier plateau can
請問那個輕障高原的山可以
so high
如此的高
Then the plateau can be like this
然後高原可以如此的
such a large area
如此的大面積
and then in the world there is no
然後是在世界上面卻沒有
One is that the area of ​​a plateau can be so large
一個就是一個高原面積可以那麼大
a mountain
一個高山
Mountains that grow every year
就一年一長出來的山脈
mountains can be taller than them
高山可以比他們高
What are his conditions?
請問他有什麼條件呢
there are several answers
有好幾個答案可以回答
English
英文
because there is no standard answer
因為沒有標準答案
What are the conditions?
那有什麼條件呢?
I have studied this Tibet for many years
這個西藏我因為研究了很多年
when i spoke from the beginning
我從一開始講的時候
The questions you ask are all questions that I want to solve or answer
你問的問題都是我想解決或者回答的問題
or a question that many people want to answer
或者很多人想回答的問題
So every time I started doing it ten years ago
所以我每次在我十年前開始做的時候
Every speech should say these things
每次演講都要講這些東西
But because I've been talking for so many years
但是因為講了那麼多年
so i forget about him now
所以我現在都忘記他
or don't want to talk about it
或者不想去講這個東西
Because no one has been able to answer so far
因為沒有人能夠回答到目前為止
It seems a bit arrogant to say that.
這樣說好像有點傲慢的回答
But there are many difficult answers in the middle
但中間有很多難回答
Like one of our opponents, a professor at UCL called Harrison
像我們的對手之一 UCL的一位教授叫做Harrison
He often said that Tibet is unique in his speeches
他常常在演講裡面就說西藏是unique
so do tibetan research
所以做西藏研究
There is no way to apply to any other shape in
沒辦法apply到其他任何的造型在
Any other shape gaining knowledge
其他任何造型在得到的知識
There is no way to apply to Tibet
也沒辦法apply到西藏來
So this is the core part of your question
所以這就是你剛才的問題裡面的核心部分
This is UCL
這就是UCL
The so-called big name is called the National Academy of Sciences
所謂的大牌叫做美國國家科學院士
How dare he speak so loudly
他敢說那麼大聲的話
Why is the new assembly so high?
那新大會怎麼那麼高
Simply put, India collides with Asia
簡單的時候就是印度跟亞洲相碰撞
indian asian crash
印度亞洲碰撞
So India started colliding around 60 million years ago
所以印度在6千萬年左右開始碰撞
but after the collision
但是碰撞以後
The speed still continues to be measured according to the current GPS global satellite positioning
速度仍然繼續按照現在的那個GPS全球衛星定位的測量
It still continues to make relative motion to the north at the speed of 4 cm every year
它還是繼續每年以4公分的那個速度往北做相對運動
didn't quite stop
並沒有完全停下來
So the category that pushes north is obviously the main support
所以那個往北推的那個類量顯然是主要支撐
Why can support Tibet be folded up so high
支撐西藏為什麼可以攏起來那麼高
then always
然後一直
High spin does not collapse there
高旋在那裡不垮下來
According to the model of mountain movement, it means that the mountain grows to a certain height
如果照山運動的那個模式的話是說山長到一定的高度
When the balance of variety shows cannot be maintained
綜藝均衡沒辦法維持的時候
it's going to collapse
它要垮塌下來
But Tibet is very strange
但是西藏是很奇怪
It has been maintained for 5 or 6 ten million years, but it will not collapse for 50 or 60 million years
維持了5、6十個百萬年就5、6千萬年還不肯垮下來
There must be some special mechanism
必須要有一些特殊的那個機制
So there are many special mechanisms
所以有很多特殊的機制
Including our article also thought about some
包括我們的文章裡面也想了一些
let me explain
來解釋啊
But this one has a lot of details
但是這個有很多太細節的部分
So if you are really interested
所以你如果真的有興趣的話
That doesn't seem to be very respectful of your question.
這樣子好像對你的問題不太尊敬
If you want to know more details
如果你想知道更多的細節的話
maybe after that is over
也許等一下那個完理後
I can specifically explain some details to you
我可以再專門的再多解釋一些細節給你聽
okay
好嗎
In this way, can I have to take a class before I can speak?
這樣子我可不可以要上一堂課才可以講嗎
Come to the Department of Geology, National Taiwan University
來讀台大地質系啦
sorry professor
教授不好意思
Can I ask you some historical gossip
可不可以跟您問一些歷史上的八卦
I know where the voice comes from
在哪裡出聲音我都很認了
later
後面
OK good
OK 好
you just mentioned that
您剛剛有提到那個
On the holy mountain there may be Noah Fang
聖山上可能有諾雅芳州挺靠
not i mentioned
不是我提到
stories in the bible
聖經裡面的故事
The holy mountain mentioned in Noah Fang State is that mountain
諾雅芳州提到的聖山就是那個山
Don't know means you are in the process of investigating
不知道就是說您在調查過程當中
is there some history
是不是有一些歷史
There are some foundational governments on earth that can prove
就是有一些地上的一些基政可以證實
No
沒有
is indirect
就是間接
then you can you just mentioned
那您可以您剛剛有提到
I don’t know if you have heard some stories that are different from the Greek mythology we read in the local investigation
不曉得你在當地調查有沒有聽到一些跟我們讀到的那個希臘神話不太一樣的故事
You didn't either She didn't even have the Trojan horse and now the new Trojan horse looks ugly
你也沒有 她連那個木馬都不見了 現在新蓋的木馬看起來很醜
It's better in the movie
電影裡面拍得比較好
the problem is
那問題是
Thank you teacher for your wonderful speech. The question I want to ask the teacher is in the history of the earth.
謝謝老師精采的演講 我想要請問老師的問題是在地球歷史上
Has there ever been a plateau as large as Tibet?
是不是曾經出現過像西藏這麼大規模的高原
Same question as him, tried not to answer, and here you are again
跟他的問題一樣 設法不要回答了 結果你又來了
But Mr. Luo Xinghua, a graduate of our fourth department, is a student and is now a teacher at the University of Hong Kong.
但是我們第四系的畢業生羅興華老師是學生 現在在香港大學的老師
The University of Hong Kong is called that question that is so difficult to answer
香港大學叫做說要問那麼難答的那個問題
There are many speculations or guesses whether there is a similar situation with Tibet
有很多推測或猜測是不是跟西藏有類似的情況
One of the conjectures is that the mainland scholars said that China's North China
其中一個推測的是大陸的學者說的說中國的華北
North China Block 或North China Crayton
North China Block 或North China Crayton
During the Mesozoic Era, because of the collision of the North China road blocks
在中生代的時候 因為華北路塊碰撞的時候
May have been so tall by Taiwanese
可能曾經被台人那麼高過
There are many low thickenable speech like
有很多低可增厚的演講像
Ela Kaiz That Formation
Ela Kaiz那個形成
So they said that once in the Zhongzheng Dynasty
所以他們說曾經在中正代的時候
had the eastern part of china
有過中國的東部
There used to be a plateau as large as Tibet
有過像西藏那麼大規模的高原
but only explanations or doctrines
但是只是解釋或者學說
or speculation
或者是推測
yes many people believe
是有很多人相信
There are also many people who do not believe
也有很多人不相信
Then apply it to the past history of the earth
那同樣Apply到地球過去歷史裡面
because the time is longer
因為時間更長遠的話
This is the problem of geological record keeping.
這個就有那個地質紀錄保存的問題
so it's hard to really do a direct comparison
所以很難很難真正做直接的對比
So I still can't answer you
所以仍然回答不了你了
some problems
有的問題
problem to i have a problem
問題到我有一個問題
you come as a tour guide
你來當作導遊
We use the guide this geologist's
我們用導遊這個地質學家的
It shows that Huangshan in the Huangshan mainland is very famous
說明這個黃山大陸的黃山很有名
I haven't been there yet
我還沒去過
Granite Huangshan
花崗岩的黃山
Like the mountain in Zhangjiajie
跟這個張家界的那種山
That geology is very famous
那個地質學都很有名的
I thought you were there
我以為你去過而已
Have you ever been to Zhangjiajie?
張家界的你去過沒有
nor
也沒有
then you go
那你去
I've been there
那我都去過
The three mountains are different
那三種山都不一樣
he might be able to speak better for me
他可能可以幫我說得好一點
The geology of Huangshan and the mountains of Zhangjiajie
黃山的地質跟張家界的山
it was the sea
本來是海嘛
then the table rises
然後台升起來
then bluestone
然後青石
Then the geology is different
然後那種地質都不一樣
Huangshan is Huajiangyan
黃山是有華江岩
Hua Jiangyan’s words are actually similar to South China’s
華江岩的話其實跟華南
The one in the southeast of China
整個中華東南邊的那個
When Zhou Shen took
在周深帶的時候
very broad
很廣泛
Especially in the second season of Bai
特別是在白二季的時候
Very extensive Huaganyan activities are related
很廣泛的花幹岩活動有關係
Nahua Dry Rock Activities
那花幹岩活動
At that time, the general explanation was that
那個時候一般的解釋是說
When in Zhongzheng belt
在中正帶的時候
At that time there was the ancient Pacific Ocean
那個時候有古太平洋
Four percent of the ocean in the ancient Pacific
古太平洋的海洋百分之四朝
Submerged in the northwest direction
西北方向做隱沒作用的
So in the southeast of what is now China
所以在現在中國的東南邊
the southeastern edge of Asia
也就是亞洲的東南邊緣
Formed a time like the Antize Hills
形成一個當時像安蒂茲山
something like that
那個樣子的東西
So the flower dry rock in Huangshan is
所以黃山的那個花幹岩是
A bunch of flower dry rock activities
一大堆花幹岩活動
A product of the Huochen activity looks like this
火塵活動裡面的一個產物這樣子
Then he is Hualei Rock
那他是花蕾岩
So the position he invaded
所以他侵入的那個位置
The flower bud rock in Huangshan should not be so deep at the beginning
當初黃山的花蕾岩應該沒有那麼深
It should be at a depth of five to ten kilometers
應該是五到十公里的那個深度
So the five to ten kilometers on the surface
所以那個地表上五到十公里的
After the crust peeled off
那個地殼剝落了以後
Then he lays on top of that
然後他鋪入到那個上面
As for why Huangshan looks so good-looking
至於他黃山為什麼長得那麼好看
This is beyond the scope of address science
這個超過地址學的範圍
I can't help you pour oil
我沒辦法幫你倒油
That Zhangjialu is a dungeon
那張家綠是地城
I found that I eat food so far away
發現我吃菜這麼遠去
but because i've been
但是因為我去過
The Danxia Mountain in Guangdong
廣東的那個丹霞山
if you have been
如果你有去過的話
Those who haven't been can go and see
沒有去過的人可以去看
That too
那也是
not exactly similar
不是完全相似的
But it’s basically the same dungeon with minor differences
但是基本是大同小異的那個地城
It was from the time of the Mesozoic Era
當初是從中生代那個時候
The mainland in South China is a stable one
在華南那個大陸是一個穩定的那個
platform is called platform
platform叫地台
There are a lot of
地台的時候上面有很多
The itinerary with a lot of limestone in Lampton
Lampton很多石灰岩的那個行程
and then at the same time some
然後同時有一些
The dungeon itinerary in Silent Rock
沉寂岩的那個地城行程
but then
但後來
The so-called orogeny from Baierji to the Cenozoic Era
所謂的經過白二季一直到新生代的一些造山運動
It took a lot of talking about that orogeny
那個造山運動說來要花很多口舌
Because many experts have different models
因為很多專家有不同的模型
So I better not be exposed in it
所以我最好不要引露在裡面
Then it starts from the Shenxi environment of the diving sea
然後它從潛海的沉溪環境
Then it became the present land heart
然後變成現在的陸地內心
Then mainly Taiwan is born above sea level
然後主要就是台生到海平面以上
If the Taiwan grows above sea level, it will accept erosion
台生到海平面以上的話就是要接受侵蝕作用
As long as the principle is below sea level
只要原理是在海平面以下的話
You are Think
你就是Think
You can accept Luyuan to Shenxi environment there
你可以接受路源來沉溪環境在那裡
But once above sea level
但是一旦超過海平面
you become more than erosion benchmarks equal to
你就變超過侵蝕基準等於是
You become the source of erosion
你就變成是侵蝕的Source
Then start to accept the later erosion
然後就開始接受後期的侵蝕作用
Probably it should be like this
大概情況應該是這樣的
Okay, thank you
好,謝謝
is there any problem
那還有沒有什麼問題
teacher, i want to ask
老師我想請教一下
You just said you could know a certain rock
你剛剛都說你可以知道某個岩石
Travel a few kilometers below the surface
去地表下幾公里行程
then i want to know which one
那我想知道是那個
How does he know how many kilometers he travels?
他是幾公里行程他是要怎麼知道
Thanks
謝謝
A few kilometers of travel, for example, in the case of Huaganye
幾公里行程譬如說花甘野的話
Kanno has some special minerals
花甘野會有一些特殊的礦物
Special minerals are most common
特殊的礦物最常見
do we have walls of kangaroo here
我們這裡有花甘野的牆壁嗎
Or have you seen that kangaroo has three main minerals
或者你們有看過花甘野有三種主要的礦物
his name is mineralogy
他叫礦物學
with quartz
有石英
is a transparent mineral
是個透明的礦物
So the one in Huakanye
所以那個在花甘野裡面的
translucent or transparent mineral
半透明或者很透明的那個礦物
The most transparent mineral is quartz
最透明的礦物就是石英
In addition to quartz, there is a white mineral called feldspar
石英以外還有白色的礦物叫長石
Feldspar is opaque but mainly white so that sometimes it will be a little hairy
長石是那個不透明的但是主要是白到有時候會有點發
the red mineral
紅的那個礦物
And then there's another mineral called Feather Mother
然後還有一個礦物叫做羽母
The feather mother is black and easy to see, often in pieces
羽母是黑的很容易看常常是一片一片的
will see these minerals
會看到這些礦物
Except that this mineral is sometimes compared
除了這個礦物有時候比較
We call it the more neutral Huakanye
我們叫比較中性一點的花甘野
In fact, you will see in diorite or diorite diorite
其實會到閃長岩或者花甘閃長岩裡面你會看到
A black mineral called amphibole
一種黑色的礦物叫腳閃石
foot amphibole sure you have a chance to see if you go
腳閃石肯定你有機會看到如果你去
Datun Mountain, Yangming Mountain, National Park
大屯山、陽明山、國家公園
Look at those words of Anshan eye
你們看那些安山眼的話
you can easily see stepping stones
你很容易就看到腳踏石
how do we know its intrusive formation
我們怎麼知道它侵入的形成
What about the cooling temperature and pressure of the magma?
那個岩漿冷卻的溫度跟壓力呢
to analyze the minerals in it
去分析這裡面的礦物
especially stepping stones or mica
特別是腳踏石或者是雲母
feldspar composition
再相當長石的成分
Feldspar these minerals
長石這些礦物裡面
There is a mass of elements
有一些元素的海量
It is related to temperature and pressure
是跟溫度跟壓力有一定的對比關係的
So according to this comparison
所以按照這個對比關係
We can build something called a geothermometer
我們可以建立一些叫做地質溫度計
or geometer stuff
或地質壓力計的東西
So look at some special minerals in it
所以看它裡面的某一些特殊礦物裡面的
What is the mass of chemical composition
化學成分的海量是多少
We can calculate its equilibrium temperature and equilibrium pressure
我們可以計算它的平衡的溫度跟平衡的壓力
like this
這樣子的話
pressure from balance
從平衡的壓力
How deep can we push it
我們就可以推它的深度是多少
So we can put this rock mass
所以可以把這個岩體
or the temperature and pressure at which this rock crystallizes or cools
或這個岩石結晶或冷卻的溫度跟壓力
can be calculated
可以計算出來
no difference from now on
從現在無差
No difference, because it's too much trouble to hold hands
無差那樣因為牽手到太多麻煩了
so that detail
所以那個細節
Thanks
謝謝
Well, if there's no problem, we have one more
好 沒有問題的話 我們還有一個
Teacher, listened to so much heavy stuff tonight
老師 今天晚上聽了這麼多沉重的東西
I want to ask a simple question
我想問一個比較粗淺的問題
I'm curious, since when did the teacher become interested in stones?
那個 我很好奇 老師是從什麼時候開始對石頭有興趣
something so hard and so hard
這麼辛苦又這麼硬的東西
how can it be so funny
怎麼會變得這麼有趣呢
Because I think many children will come to participate today
因為我想今天有很多小朋友來參加
they are
他們是
The standard answer is that I became interested after I entered the Department of Geology at National Taiwan University
標準答案就是我進了台大地質系以後開始有興趣
just started
才開始的
Actually no, I wasn’t very interested in it when I entered the Department of Geology at National Taiwan University.
其實不是 進了台大地質系的時候還不怎麼有興趣
My senior is here, he might fine me at this time
我的學長在這裡 他這時候可能罰我
I didn't know what to do until after I graduated from college
一直到我大學畢業以後還不曉得該做什麼
At that time I wanted to be a soldier
那個時候想去當文兵
just give society to do something else
就給出社會去做一些其他事
but i met a good teacher
但是我碰到一個很好的老師
My teacher is Chen Zhenhong
我的老師叫陳振宏
Maybe you've heard his name
也許你們聽過他的名字
He was the former vice chairman of Congress
他是前一任的國會副主委
If you've ever watched the congressional news
如果你有看過國會新聞的話
Called Hi by Chen Zhenhong
被陳振宏叫做嗨
so let me go to his grad school
所以讓我去讀他的研究生
And from then on that one went on this road of no return
然後從此以後那個走上了這個不歸路
Only discovered after the point of no return
不歸路以後才發現
interested in this
興趣這個東西
Maybe it's not necessarily what I wanted to do when I was a child
也許是不一定是從小就要怎麼樣
specially bred
特別培養的
when you infoed in it
當你infoed在裡面
and found inside
然後發現裡面
there are some fun things
居然有一些好玩的東西
At least you can go sightseeing, right?
至少可以遊山玩水嘛對不對
But some people don't like traveling
但是有的人不喜歡遊山玩水
On the contrary, I feel that it is very hard to go there.
反而覺得去那裡很辛苦
like many kids nowadays
像現在很多小孩
No, no, a kid from the Department of Geology, National Taiwan University
不不不 台大地質系的小孩
You have to ask him to climb that mountain
你要叫他去爬那個山
or go there to play
或到那個地方去玩
he will find it fun
他會覺得很好玩
There are many homeboys and homegirls in the Geology Department of National Taiwan University
就有很多宅男宅女在台大地質系裡面
If you also like to travel in mountains and rivers
如果你也喜歡遊山玩水
Must be ranked
必排之中
if running outside
如果是在外面跑的話
In fact, geology or technical science
其實地質學或是技術科學學
there should be many
應該有很多
The interests that can be cultivated are in it
可以培養的興趣在裡面
That's why I became interested after I entered the Geology Department of National Taiwan University.
所以我進來台大地質系以後才有興趣的
actually right
其實沒錯
The so-called gas station on the ground is completely out of the field, which is very hard.
地上所謂油站完整的出野外非常辛苦的
no air condition
沒有air condition
There may not be breakfast, there may not be anything
不一定有早餐的不一定有什麼的
It's hard work being outside
出野外是非常辛苦的
Assuming a joke, I went to Sumen University to run wild at the beginning of a year
假設笑話我一年初到蘇門大大去跑野外
with one of my new postdocs
帶著我的一個新的博士後
Then after renting for one night, he told me the next day
然後租了一晚以後他第二天就跟我說
Why doesn't this hotel have a shower head in the bathroom
為什麼這個旅館的浴室裡面沒有蓮蓬頭
OK, we finally thank Mr. Dong for his wonderful speech
OK 我們最後謝謝東老師精彩的演講
let's be a lot of rocks
讓我們就是很多石頭
Thank you puffs thank you
謝謝你們的蓬蓬 謝謝
You
You